<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon vpon the xii. xiij, and xiiij. verses of the xiiij. chapter of Ezechiel Wherein are chiefly shewed both the originall &amp; accidentall causes of euerie dearth and famine, and especially of this dearth in England now 1608. and 1609. With the effects and fruites of the same, as also the helpes &amp; remedies therof, if they be speedily and effectually practised. Preached at Strowd in the countrie of Glocester and published for the good of the church melitant. Whereunto is added a like meditation of the same author, vpon the 26. verse of the 11. chapter of Salomons Prouerbs, which may be called the Poore mans plea. By William Woodwall, minister and preacher of the word. 1609</title>
            <author>Woodwall, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104842</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840573</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840573</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5091</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15694)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5091)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 863:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon vpon the xii. xiij, and xiiij. verses of the xiiij. chapter of Ezechiel Wherein are chiefly shewed both the originall &amp; accidentall causes of euerie dearth and famine, and especially of this dearth in England now 1608. and 1609. With the effects and fruites of the same, as also the helpes &amp; remedies therof, if they be speedily and effectually practised. Preached at Strowd in the countrie of Glocester and published for the good of the church melitant. Whereunto is added a like meditation of the same author, vpon the 26. verse of the 11. chapter of Salomons Prouerbs, which may be called the Poore mans plea. By William Woodwall, minister and preacher of the word. 1609</title>
                  <author>Woodwall, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 68, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. A[llde] for Ed. White, &amp; are to be solde at his shop neere the little North doore of S. Paules church at the Signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>G2r has caption title, reading: A prouerbe pronounced to all the cruell, couetous, and hard hearted corne-maisters, cloath-maisters, and al other olde pinching penny-fathers at this day amongst vs, who esteem more of their vnrighteous Mammon then of the counsell of Christ our beloved Sauiour, who aduertiseth them to make them friends therof in due time, that they might be receiued into euerlasting tabernacles and yet will not.</note>
                  <note>H1 has caption title, reading: A meditation vpon the 26. verse of the 11. chap. of the Prouerbes; which may fitly be called, The poore-mans plea.</note>
                  <note>print show-through, and some pages stained; leaf K1 is a facsimile.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Wealth --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5091:1"/>
            <p>SERMON Vpon the xii. xiij. and xiiij. Verſes of the xiiij. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Ezechiel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein are chiefly ſhewed both the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall</hi> &amp; accidentall cauſes of euerie dearth and famine, and eſpecially of this dearth in England now 1608. and 1609. With the effects and Fruites of the ſame, as alſo the helpes &amp; remedies ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if they may be ſpeedily and effectually pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed.</p>
            <p>Preached at STROWD in the Countie of Gloceſter and publiſhed for the good of the church Melitant.</p>
            <p>Wherunto is added a like Meditation of the ſame <hi>Author, upon the 26. verſe of the 11. Chapter of</hi> Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Prouerbs, <hi>which may be called the Poore mans plea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By William</hi> WOODWALL, <hi>Miniſter and Preacher of the word.</hi> 1609</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by E. A. for <hi>Ed. White,</hi> &amp; are to be ſolde at his ſhop neere the ltttle North doore of S. Paules Church at the Signe of the Gunne 1609</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5091:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5091:2"/>
            <head>TO His Chriſtian Bretheren of the Clergie, Grace, Mercy, and Peace from God our heauenly Father, by Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>or as much as euerie true Miniſter is the Lords watch-man, and thereapon bound by the band of obedience towards God, to blow the Trumpet, and warne the people, when he ſeeth the ſword of the Lord come uppon the land, that is, the Plague of Peſtilence, dearth, Famine, War, or any ſuchlike: and for that I haue not hitherto ſeene or heard of anye warning giuen by any brother in publike of this ſword of the lord laide uppon this land, by dearth of Corne and other commedities, although I eſteemed my ſelfe the moſte unworthie of all others, yet I could not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde from the publiſhing of this little paper-worke, hoping that it might be a motine unto thoſe that are better able to take this matter in hand, or at leaſt a diſcharge unto my ſelf of that Talent that God hath giuen me, the which name end enour if it pleaſe Almightie God to bleſse, I ſhall account my trauel wel baſtowed. Let that ſaying therefore of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> Ezekiel <hi>written in the</hi> 33. Ch. ver. 7. &amp; 8, <hi>be alwaies before thee, &amp; in thy minde.</hi> So thou O ſonne of man, I
<pb facs="tcp:5091:3"/> haue made thee a watch-man vnto the houſe Iſrael, Therefore thou ſhalt heare the word at my mouth, and admoniſh them from me, when I ſhall ſay vnto the wicked, O wicked man, thou ſhalt die the death, if thou dooſt not ſpeake, nor admoniſh the wicked of his way, that wicked in an ſhall dye for his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but his blood will I require at thy hands. <hi>By both which doctrines or leſsons of the Lord, we are taught how needfull and neceſſary a thing it is for the Miniſter of God to beſtir himſelf both in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, in the work and word of the Lord. A ſorry watchman would he be counted of his Captaine, that being ſet to watch the Citty, would ſleep in the night and play in the day, and let the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my come in which way he would: ſo careles no doubt are many at this day amongst us, who being ſet to watch ouer the houſe of the Lord, let the lords enemies come in and out, which way they liſt. For could there ſuch crueltie or coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes abound as doth, or ſuch dearth and fam in encreaſe as is like to be, if the Trumpet of Gods word were well ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the people of this land duely admoniſhed? no, no, it could not be, but ſome hearts would be opened: for doth not the Lord complaine that his people are deſtroyed for lack of knowledge?</hi> Hoſ. 4. 6. <hi>&amp; could they or would they commit ſuch things as are dayly don amongst vs, if they were right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admoniſhed of the ſame? Therfore looke unto it my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren, that ye be not found negligent in the worke of the Lord, I ſay, that ye be not hot nor cold, but zealous for the Lords glorie. Gine the Lord no reſt day nor night, but call upon him continually, call upon them likewiſe that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to your charge, that euery man may know his own</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5091:3"/> 
               <hi>diſeaſe, and break off ſins by repeat once, and do the work of the Lord faithfully, as it becometh good diſpoſers of thoſe treaſures committed unto your truſt, not looking ſo much unto thoſe things that concerne your own eſtate in this life, as unto the things of the Lord Ieſus, his flocke, his lambes, his ſheepe, his People, his Chruch, his king dome; which grace the Lord grant us for his Chriſts ſake.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine now and alwaies in the feare of God. W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:5091:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5091:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON vpon the 12. 13. and 14. Verſes of the 14. Chapter of EZECHIEL.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>THE TEXT.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p n="12">12, The word of the Lord came vnto me, ſaying:</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Sonne of man, when the land ſinneth againſt mee by committing a treſpaſſe, then wil I ſtretch out my hand vppon it, and wil breake the ſtaffe of the bread thereof, and wil ſend famine vpon it.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. <hi>Though theſe three men</hi> Noah, Daniel <hi>and</hi> Iob <hi>were among them, they ſhold deliuer but their owne ſoules by their righteouſneſſe, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He word of the Lord came vnto me, ſaying:</hi> Out of this whole text, do ariſe three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall or eſpeciall points right neceſſary of vs to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered, both in regard of our owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and admonition, as alſo in reſpect of the time preſent; it beeing a time of dearth and ſcarſitie, and hunger amongſt vs, as that was a time of trouble amongſt the Iſraelites,
<pb facs="tcp:5091:5"/> when the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> vtttered theſe wordes vnto them, ſo that this text or parcell of Scripture, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Of the word ſpoken in his place or ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Whichis like apples of gold with pictures of ſiluer,</hi> meaning, that as the one is pleaſant to the eye to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde and looke vppon, ſo the other is or ought to be as pleaſant and delectable to the eare, heart, and minde of man to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of, &amp; ponder vpon, or like vnto the emplaiſter or potio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is rightly imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the learned and skilfull phiſition, and expert chirurgian, to the party diſeaſed or member affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For as we ſay, to come in time is the chiefeſt thing of al, ſo to ſpeak in time, that is, aptly &amp; to the purpoſe, is a point very commendable and no leſſe profitable. The principall points or parts heerein to be handled, are theſe: Firſt, what is both the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall and accidental cauſe of dearth or famine, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the 13. verſe, &amp; firſt part thereof. Secondly what be the effects and fruits thereof, laide down in the latter part of that v. Thirdly what be the helps &amp; remedies of euery ſuch dearth, plague, or iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, which are ſhewed &amp; ſet down in the 15. v. But before I can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniently come to entreat of theſe 3. I muſt giue you a taſte of ſome other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſuch as by the way of a preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the reſt are deſcribed by this prophet, in the 12. v. as namely what he meaneth by ſaying, <hi>The word of the lord came vnto me,</hi> the maner how it came, from whome and vnto whome; for like as euery Embaſſador heere on earth, which is ſent from one Prince or Potentate to another, vpon any embaſſie or meſſage, doth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his or their firſt arriuall vnto the perſon to whome
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5091:5"/> they are ſent, make knowne both who ſent him, and wherefore, as well for the further credit of his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, as for the better acceptation of himſelfe; euen ſo doth this man of God the prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> in this place (being called of God to deliuer his word vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the children of Iſrael) as it is to be ſeene more at large in the 1. 2. 3. ch. of this propheſie; doth in theſe words make knowne vnto them, not onely what he was to ſay vnto them, or what Embaſſage he was to deliuer, but alſo who had ſent him, and whoſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador hee was, as out of the words of this text may be gathered. <hi>The word of the Lord came vnto me,</hi> Becauſe euerie word of this text is verye patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, I wil intreat of them <hi>verbatim</hi> (as they ſay) as they come in order. And firſt, wheras he entituleth his meſſage by the title or name of (the word of the Lord) it giueth vs to vnderſtand of ſome neceſſarie points to be conſidered of, as namely, and firſt of al, what the word of the Lord is, &amp; what he meaneth thereby in this place: Secondly what the dignitie oc excellencie thereof is: Thirdly what is the vtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and laſt of all the neceſſitie.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt point what it is, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in the whole, it is reuerenced with many ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, as the Lambes booke: the Librarie of the holy Ghoſt: fountaines of Iſrael, waters of life: the two edged ſword, <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thumim.</hi> So it being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in part, is called the power of God vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, to euerie one that beleeueth. But what the Prophet meaneth in this place by it, you muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 16.</note> that he meaneth no other thing but onely an holy Leſſon, counſell, Doctrine or admonition,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5091:6"/> or elſe an earneſt and ſharpe commination and dreadefull denunciation of Gods iudgement (ſuch as is contaiued in theſe words which I haue reade vnto you) inſpired or taught of God himſelfe, that is, by his holy ſpirit, for their inſtruction, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, or amendment, to whome it was then ſent, as likewiſe vnto vs, &amp; the church militant, to whom it ſhold at any time hereafter be preached. And this is both the meaning and ſignification of it in this place. Now concerning the dignitie or excellencie therof, although there can be no greater a praiſe or commendation be giuen thereof, then that which you haue alredy heard. <hi>Ro.</hi> 1. 16. &amp;c. Yet becauſe the word it ſelfe is pregnant in this point, it ſhall not be teadious vnto me to giue ſome taſt therof. Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie therefore is that to be called to minde that the Prophet DAVID hath left recorded in Pſ. 19. ver. 7. 8. &amp;c. ſaying: <hi>The law of the Lord is perfect conuerting the ſoule; the teſtimonie of the Lord is ſure, and giueth wiſdom vnto the ſimple: the ſtatutes of the Lord are right and reioice the heart: the Commaundements of the Lord are true and righteous altogether, more to be deſired then golde, yea then much fine golde: ſweeter then honye and the hony combe, yea dearer vnto me then thouſands of gold and ſiluer.</hi> All which is ſpoken of the word of the Lord, either in generall or particular, or in both, that men might make good vſe thereof, and giue good regard thereunto, when it is ſent or preached vnto them. A common fault amongſt manye at this day, which eſteeme of it no better then of a tale of Robinhood, or as this Prophet ſheweth of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in his time, Ch. 33. ve. 31. 32. who eſteemed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5091:6"/> none otherwiſe then of a ſong of one that hath a pleaſant voice to ſing wel, for the vtilitie or profit thereof. The Apoſtle Saint PAVL will tell vs, that the whole Scripture is giuen by inſpiration of God and is profitable to teach, to conuince, to correct, and to inſtruct in righteouſnes, that the man of god may be abſolute and perfect vnto all good workes. 2. Tim. 3. ver. 16. 17. And Saint IAMES will ſay that it is able to ſaue our ſoules if it bee receiued with meekenes. 1. IAM. 1. 21. And for the neceſſitie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, let that be remembred which Salomon hath left recorded; namely, that where the word of the Lord is not preached, there the people periſh, <hi>but he that keepeth the law ſhall be bleſſed,</hi> Pro. 29. 18. Theſe things being thus laide down, doe giue vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not onelye what it is that heere the Prophet hath to ſay, but alſo who this Lord is, whoſe word is ſo powerfull, precious &amp; profitable: for although he is heere but barelye named Lord, without anye further addition of this Title or declaration of his Maieſtie; yet this his word heere mentioned (if we will ſearch it well) will teach vs and tell vs, that it is euen that Lord of Lords, and King of Kinges, that onely hath immortallitie, and dwelleth in light that <note place="margin">Reu. 17. 14 1. Timo. 6. 16 Pſ. 50. 1.</note> none can attaine vnto, whome neuer man ſawe nor can ſee, vnto whome bee honour &amp; power euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Amen. Euen the God of Gods, the Lord who hath ſpoken and called the earth from the riſing vp of the Sunne, vnto the going downe thereof. The Lord of hoaſts who buildeth his ſphears in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and hath laide the foundation of his Globe of <note place="margin">Aug. 9. 6.</note> elements in the earth. He calleth the waters of the Sea, and powreth them out vpon the earth.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:5091:7"/>
            <p>The Lord is his name <hi>(Came vnto me)</hi> How, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what manner this word or meſſage of the Lord came vnto the prophet EZECHIEL, not only him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſheweth moſte plainely, Chap. 1. verſe 3. and 29. Whereas he teſtifieth that the hand of the Lord was vpon him: that is, the ſpirit of Propheſie, and that he heard a voice of one that ſpake to him: But alſo the Authour to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> Chap. 1. verſe. 1. 2 teacheth that the Almightie God at ſundrie times and in diuers maners, ſpake in olde time to our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the Prophets, as in the firſt age to the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes by himſelfe perſonally; as to ABRAHAM, MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SES, &amp;c. So afterwards to the Prophets ESAY, IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REMIE, EZECHIEL and the reſt, by dreames, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and inſpirations. But in the fulneſſe of time (which the Apoſtle calles the laſt daies,) hath hee ſpoken to vs by his Sonne, whome hee hath made heyre of all things, like as in theſe our daies (which are the laſt daies indeed) he doth ſpeake vnto vs, the holy miniſters of his word, as vnto your ſelues by vs, by his holy and diuine ſpirit, according as the Prophet IOEL fore-tolde. Cha. 2. 28. ſaying: <hi>And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe daies I will poure out of my ſpirit vpon all fleſh, &amp; your Sonnes and your Daughters ſhall propheſie, and your olde men ſhall dreame dreames, and your yong men ſhall ſee viſions.</hi> Agreeable, whereunto our Sauiour in the goſpel ſaith, <hi>Mat. 23. 34. Behold I ſend vnto you prophets and wiſemen, and Scribes &amp;c.</hi> And againe, <hi>it is not you that ſpeake but the ſpirit of your heauenly father that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in you. Mat.</hi> 10 20. From whence commeth this obſeruation, that our moſte gratious God in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hath had ſuch a care in building vp his Church, that he hath vouchſafed to ſpeake vnto the ſame, &amp;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5091:7"/> to ſend forth labourers into his vineyard from time to time, that like as in the beginning &amp; creation of all things, he ſaid <hi>Let there be light, &amp; there was light, let there be a firmament, &amp;c.</hi> I ſay, as in the creation of the materiall frame and ſubſtance of this externall and viſible world, God made al things by his word, (for he ſpake the word and they were made) Pſ. 148. 5. So in the new regeneration &amp; building vp of the New Ireuſalem, he ſendeth forth his word, that is, he ſpeaketh by his ſpirit in the heartes &amp; mindes of his holy Miniſters, that they ſhould ſpeake vnto the congregation that which he enioyneth them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond obſeruation is, that in as much as, it is not ſimply we that ſpeake vnto you, but the ſpirit of our heauenly father that ſpeaketh in vs) whereupon the Prophet ſaith: <hi>The word of the Lord came vnto me)</hi> that you yeelde ſuch attention to the word ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by vs, as vnto the word of the eternal &amp; liuing God, as Chriſt himſelfe teacheth, ſaying: <hi>He that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth you heareth me, &amp;c.</hi> Mat. 10. and that eſpeciallye becauſe we are vnto you, as this prophet was vnto the people of ISRAEL, the Embaſſadors or Legates of the Lord, as Saint PAVL plainely prooueth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Now then are we Embaſsiadors of the Lord, as though God did beſeech you through vs, wee pray you in his ſteede that you would bee reconciled vnto God, for hee that made him to be ſinne for vs, which knew no ſinne, that we might be the righteous of God through him.</hi> 2. Cor. 5. verſe 20 21. And therfore to conclude of this point, I ſay, let him that hath an eare heare what the ſpirit ſpeaketh vnto the congregation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by this we may obſerue and learne how farre foorth the Almightie God (whome the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5091:8"/> of heauens cannot hold or conteine) doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelfe, to our weakenes, vouchſafing to ſpeake to vs, &amp; to talk with vs familiarly, according to our capacities, whoſe voice otherwiſe is ſo migh ty &amp; ſo ſtrong, that it is compared to the thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claps which breaketh the Cedars of Libanus, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Rockes, and maketh the Mountaines to cleaue in ſunder. This the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> make plaine, who when they had heard the Lord ſpeake vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſaw the thunder and the lightning, they deſired that <hi>Moſes</hi> might ſpeake vnto them, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that if God ſpake vnto them they ſhould dye, Exo. 20. 19. ſo terrible is the voice of the immortal creator to the mortall creature. And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding for our inſtruction, admonition, &amp; amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he vouchſafeth to ſpeake vnto man, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſencibly, &amp; ſometimes ſecretly euen in his eare, as our Sauiour ſheweth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 27. ſaying <hi>Whatſoeuer you ſhall heare in the eare that is whatſoeuer I ſhall priuately by my ſelfe, or ſecretly by my ſpirit inſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your eares, hearts or mindes</hi> (for thus doth the word of the Lord come vnto vs at this day) I meane the knowledge &amp; intelligence of his word, euen when we are lying in our beds, walking on the way, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on our bookes, or otherwiſe ſequeſtred from the affaires of this world, in reading, preaching, meditating, or conferring, Then I ſay, are our hearts aſcending vp to God, and his ſpirit diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding downe to vs, as the Angels on <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder, for euen as the naturall mans delight is in thoſe things wherein his corrupted nature taketh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, And as the worldely minded mans
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5091:8"/> thoughts, do runne vpon his monies and his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, his buyings, buildings, bargaines, brab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, profits, pleaſures, or any ſuch like va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities:</p>
            <p>Euen ſo are the ſpirituall mans cogitations, totally and continually exerciſed, and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the lawe of the Lord, and in the miſteries of godlines, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> manifeſteth, in the firſt pſ. v. 3. where he ſhewing how the godly man beſtoweth his talent, ſaith <hi>That his delight is in the lawe of the lord, and in that law doth exerciſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe both day and night.</hi> Or if at any time he doth ſtoope ſo low, as to aſſociate or buſie himſelfe with the affaires of this worlde, as to eat, drinke, talke, walke, laugh, buy, ſell, or recreate himſelfe with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the creatures (for that cauſe ſubdued vnto vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, it is none otherwiſe, then as the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1. <hi>Co. 7. 31. Vſing this world</hi> that is this pleaſure, or that profit, <hi>as though he vſed it not,</hi> for why? his hart is ſtabliſhed in the Lord, and his principle ioy is in the holy ghoſt, I would ſay in the law of the Lord or word of God, <hi>vnto me,</hi> that is to me <hi>Ezechiel</hi> the ſtrength of the Lord (for ſo my name dooth ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie)</p>
            <p>As if he would ſay, though I be of my ſelfe a weak, poore, ſimple, &amp; ſinfull ſoule, yet by his grace I am ſuch a one as it hath pleaſed him to make choiſe of for the miniſtery of his word (for ſuch is his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to chuſe) as S. Paul ſheweth, 1, Cor. 1. 27. 28. ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>But God hath choſen the fooliſh thinges of this world to confound the thinges which are mightie, and vnnoble thinges of the World, and thinges which</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:5091:9"/> 
               <hi>are deſpiſed hath God choſen: you, and things that are not, to bring to naught things that are.</hi> So I by the Lord, (though ſmall in the ſight of man) am now called vnto this holy function, to be the Lords Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor: or thus, whereas by my naturall Parents and birth, I was the childe of death, ſinne and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (for I was defiled in the wombe and euer ſince) but now ſanctified by the Spirit of ſanctification, &amp; begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the immortal ſeed of Gods word, &amp; ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to the miniſtery therof by my heauenly father, both Name &amp; Nature is changed, and by his grace <hi>I am that I am,</hi> (ſaying:) If anye demaunde whether this ſpeech vnto the prophet was ſencible or ſecret, it is not much materiall whether either; for that God vſeth to ſpeake both waies vnto his Seruants, as before is prooued; but ſeemeth in this place ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be audible then intellectuall, as appeareth in the firſt Chapter, verſe 29. where as he ſaith, hee heard a voice of one that ſpake <hi>(Sonne of man)</hi> as if he would ſay, Thou which art but earth and aſhes, though I vouchſafe to ſpeake to thee in familiar maner, &amp; to manifeſt my glorie to thee, as in chap. 1. verſe 3. 4. 5. &amp; 6. &amp;c. Yet be not thou proud there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as ſome of thy fellowes before thee haue bene, (for knowledge puffeth vp) but rather goe and doe thy meſſage that I ſhal enioine thee: &amp; be not as IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS, who being ſent to <hi>Niniuie</hi> went to <hi>Tharſis:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as ADAM, who beeing charged not to taſte of the tree of knowledge of good and euill, taſted of the forbidden fruite: Neither as that man of God mentioned in the firſt booke of Kinges, Cap. 13. ver. 1. 2. &amp;c. that came out of <hi>Iuda,</hi> and propheſied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5091:9"/> the Alter that <hi>Ieroboam</hi> had ſet vp. Who beeing charged by the word of the Lord, not to eate breade nor drinke water, nor to turne again the ſame way that he came; who though he deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the King, requeſting him ſo to doe, yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward yeelded vnto the olde Prophet, and was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed of a Lyon for his labour. Whoſe example I counſell thee <hi>Ezechiel</hi> to marke, that thou doe not the like, leaſt I deſtroy thee before them, as I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied him before thee: for thou art of no better ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce nor ſtrength the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was, or the reſt before named; nor more able to withſtand or reſiſt mee then they were. Remember therefore that I tell thee before hand, what thou art, and who. Euen the Sonne of a finfull man; whether thou haue reſpect vnto <hi>Adam</hi> thy firſt parent, or to bnzie thine imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate parent (which ſignifieth contempt) thou art but an earthen veſſell full of contempt, more ready to diſobey then to obey my commandement, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heed. A Caueat to all the ſeruants of God how great ſoeuer their guiftes bee, that they ſhewe not themſelues careles of their calling, nor forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of their maiſters buſines, as Chriſt himſelfe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſeth, ſaying: <hi>VVhoſoeuer ſhall put his hand to this plowe</hi> (meaning the miniſterie and preaching of the word) <hi>and looke back,</hi> that is, by any kinde of negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, or diſobedience, <hi>is not fit for the Kingdome of heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I take partly to be the reaſon of this Title <hi>(Sonne of man)</hi> attributed vnto the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> &amp; as a pulback, to the end he ſhold not be too much exalted with the multitude of viſions &amp; Reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5091:10"/> (ſuch as were ſhewed vnto him at his firſt calling) as in the firſt chapter are to be ſeene. Like as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> recordeth, how in the like caſe, <hi>There was giuen vnto him the meſsenger of Sathan to buffet him,</hi> 2. Cor. 12. 7. From whence we learne, that before a man can be apt for the kingdome of heauen, I mean ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of deuine miſteries, he muſt be throughly mortified &amp; ſchooled in Gods ſchoole houſe, that is, in the furnace of ſome affliction or great deiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion; ſo as we ſee in S. <hi>Paul,</hi> at his conuerſion, how he was caſt downe to the ground, and ſtrucke blinde for three daies, &amp;c. Act. 9. 4. &amp;c. The like we read of <hi>Eſay,</hi> whoſe mouth was touched with a fire coale taken from the Alter: that is, ſanctified and regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by Gods ſpirit, before his iniquitie could be taken away, and his ſins purged, that he might be worthy to goe on the Lords buſines: which is or may be an aduertiſement vnto all ſuch as ſeeke to enter into the miniſtery, before they finde or feele in themſelues any ſufficient guift to diſcharge the ſame, As alſo an item to thoſe of ſuperiour place, that they admit not any into any paſtorall place or cure, that are not qualified thereunto. All which is &amp; may be comprehended &amp; included vnder this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Son of man:</hi> which title I alſo finde atributed to Ieſus Chr. as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. v. 30. &amp; 37. 44. to declare his humanity, as in this place to this prophet, to teach him his infirmitie. It followes, <hi>When the Land ſinneth againſt me,</hi> By land, heere you muſt vnderſtand the people, for the land or earth ſinneth not, how be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, it was once curſed for ſinne. A figuratiue ſpeech very vſuall in the Prophets &amp; word of God, as we
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5091:10"/> read in <hi>Eſay,</hi> Chap. 11. v. 9. &amp; 4, where it is ſayde <hi>Repleta eſt terra ſcientia domini,</hi> that is, <hi>The earth is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the knowledge of the Lord.</hi> And againe, <hi>He ſhall ſmite the earth with the rod of his mouth:</hi> where he nameth the earth, yet meaneth the people: and rod, yet meaneth the word. And ſo heere, whereas he ſaith land, it being figuratiue, giueth vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that there is more meant, then if he had ſimp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaide, the people: for it implieth not only that one ſort or part of the people, as the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers onely, or the middle part ſhould ſo ſinne againſt the Lord, but euen all: as if he ſhould ſay, both king, &amp; ſubiect, prieſt and people, poore and rich, young and olde, all which are but earth duſt and aſhes, the works of my hands, as the veſſels of clay in the hands of the potter, <hi>The land</hi> q. d. The land that I haue long time tilled and ſowne with the beſt ſeed, the land that I haue alwaies loued: or thus, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that I haue created in mine own Image, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the hands of their enemies, fed with the fineſt flower of wheat, preſerued and kept as the apple of mine eye, &amp;c. yet ſee how grieuouſly they haue ſinned againſt me, and prouoked me to wrath, in ſuch wiſe that I am ready to breake their ſtaffe of bread, therefore <hi>(Againſt me)</hi> like as it is ſaide, <hi>Mat. 12. 30. He that is not with me, is againſt me, and prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me to puniſh him:</hi> ſo contrary is ſinne vnto God, that he holdeth him to be his enemy (as it were) that committeth any ſinne.</p>
            <p>And wold not any of vs be loath to haue his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, our ſoueraigne (I meane the king of England) to be his enemie? we ſee by common experience,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5091:11"/> if a man purchaſe but the il wil of a Iuſtice of peace in his countrie, or of ſome other ſuperior perſon, how it is requited againe one time or other. But to prouoke the Lord of Hoaſtes againſt him (who is a conſuming fire) who can but looke for a requitall at his hands, who ſaith: and that of right: <hi>Reuenge is mine, and I will repay,</hi> and of whome it is alſo ſaide, <hi>It is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the Lord,</hi> As we may ſee by example, how ſeuere he hath ſhewed himſelfe euen towards his moſte deere children, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Dauid, Paul</hi> &amp; others: for can any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay but as they ſinned againſt him, ſo he puniſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for it euen to the eating of a peece of an Apple: as <hi>Saul</hi> would haue ſometime done to <hi>Ionathan</hi> for taſting a little hony, and yet good Lord what ſinnes are here committed amongſt vs on euerie ſide againſt the Lord, not in the ſinguler number as the prophet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſaying <hi>(Atreſpas)</hi> but in the plural number, euen to Milions and multitudes: it followes <hi>Then will I stretch out my hand vpon it.</hi> q. d. or declare and ſhewe foorth my power, my Iuſtice, my iudgement, and my wrath.</p>
            <p>Two manner of waies may it bee ſaide that the Lord God Almightie dooth ſtretch foorth his hand, that is to ſay, eyither to ſaue or to deſtroy, as in the 136. Pſalme, verſe 12. where it is ſaid, <hi>that hee brought out Iſraell from amongst them,</hi> (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Egiptians) <hi>with a mightie hand and ſtretched out arme.</hi> So in the Prophet <hi>Hoſe.</hi> 11. Chap: 3. verſ. <hi>I led Ephraim alſo as one ſhould beare him in his armes: but they knew not that I healed them.</hi> As <hi>Dauid</hi> againe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaith. Pſ. 77. verſe 15. <hi>Thou haſt redeemed thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5091:11"/> with thine arme, euen the Sonnes of</hi> IACOB and IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEPH.</p>
            <p>As ſince that time, how hath the Lord ſtretched out his arme for vs, and for our deliuerance, <hi>Anno</hi> 1588. when the great inuafion was pretended by the Spaniſh Nauie. And againe, ſince that 1605. when the Gun-powder treaſon was prepared for to haue made hauocke of vs all? The Lord lifted vp his mightie and ſtretched out arme for our defence and ſuccour, <hi>Oſanna</hi> his holye name haue the praiſe for it.</p>
            <p>Now as for the defence and preſeruation of his people, the Lord ſtretcheth out his arme, when they walke in his waies, and turne to him by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. So likewiſe when he intendeth to correct or puniſh his people for their Rebellions againſt him, he is ſaide to ſtretch out his hand, as we read in <hi>Iob.</hi> when Sathan ſaide to God concerning Iob. <hi>Stretch out thyne hand, and touch all that hee hath, &amp;c.</hi> q. d. <hi>puniſh and plague him. &amp;c.</hi> Likewiſe in <hi>Ieremy</hi> the 15. Chap. verſe 6. We reade thus. <hi>Thou haſt forſaken me ſaith the Lord and gone backward</hi> (meaning the Iewes) <hi>ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wil I ſtretch out my hand againſt thee, and deſtroy thee, for I am wearie of repenting. (Vppon it)</hi> By theſe words we learn, that whether they are taken literally or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiuely, that both the earth it ſelfe, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which dwell on the earth, and are earthlye min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, are in the hand of the Lord, &amp; ſubiect vnto his correction, for as he correcteth the one by famine, dearth, Peſtilence, warre, &amp;c. So hee ſmiteth the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the fruites thereof with blaſting, drought, Mildew, Caterpillers and ſuch like.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:5091:12"/>
            <p>So that to whether of either he ſtretcheth out his hand, they muſt indure and ſuffer it, which may teach vs in due time to fly vnto the lord for ſuccour, helpe and fauour, eſpecially when wee ſee his hand ſtretched fourth both towards the one &amp; the other. For not onely our ſtaffe of bread is broken, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by many of the poorer ſort of people are plagued, but alſo the earth it ſelfe is ſmitten, wherby in many places her fruites &amp; encreaſe haue failed, it cannot be denyed. <hi>(And I will breake the ſtaffe of bread therof)</hi> q. d. I will puniſh the people of that place with dearth and ſcarſitie of corne, and with hunger and famine. Theſe words are partly figuratiue as the former, &amp; therfore the more deeply to be conſidered. For ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waies is the lord ſaid to break the ſtaffe of bread, acording as I finde in his holy writ, as now I wil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto you, to the end that you may perfectlye vnderſtand the meaning of theſe wordes, and the will of the Lord contained in them.</p>
            <p>Three maner of waies doe I finde that theſe words may conueniently be taken: as firſt, when the Lord doth diminiſh or abate the fruites of the earth, as of Wheate, Barly, Rye, &amp;c. and ſo bring in a dearth &amp; famine amongſt the people, as he foretelleth by <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The Lord ſhall ſmite thee with a conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and with the Feauer, and with a burning Ague, and with feruent heate, and with the ſword, and with blaſting &amp; myldew, &amp;c.</hi> This alſo he fore-ſheweh by <hi>Ezechiel</hi> to come vpon the Iewes in their Captiuitie, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt alſo take vnto thee Wheat, &amp; Barly, and beanes, and Lintell and Millet and Vetches, and put them in a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and make thee bread thereof, according to the number</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:5091:12"/> 
               <hi>of the daies, that thou ſhalt ſleep vppon thy ſide, &amp;c.</hi> And in the 16. verſe of the ſame Chapter, he ſaith; <hi>I wil break the ſtaffe of bread in Ieruſalem, and they ſhall eate bread by weight, and drinke water by meaſure, and with astoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> meaning through the rarity &amp; ſcarſenes of Corn, &amp; this is the firſt way of breaking the Staffe of bread. And after the which way or maner, the Lord hath broken our ſtaffe of bread in ſome meaſure in this Land, by cauſing the earth to faile of her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ſome ſort of graine, as Wheate eſpecially.</p>
            <p>The ſecond way or meane, whereby the ſtaffe of breade is broken, is, when though there bee Corne ſufficient in the land, (as yet is) notwithſtanding the earth failing her encreaſe, (through the chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table aſſiſtance of ſome other Nations) yet the price therof is ſo enhaunſed and raiſed vp through the couetouſnes and cruelty of the Corn-breeders, buyers and ſellers, Conueyers and Corn-mongers, that the poore are not able to compaſſe it. And though they do for a time hold out by ſelling and pawning all that they haue, yet at the laſt they can hold out no longer, but miſerably die of the dearth and famine.</p>
            <p>Of this kinde of breaking the ſtaffe of bread, the Prophet AMOS maketh mention. Chap. 8 verſe. 4. 5. ſaying: <hi>Heare this, O ye that ſwallowe vp the poore, and make the needie of the land to faile,</hi> ſaying: <hi>When will the new Moone he gone, that we may ſell Corne? and the Sahoath, that we may ſet forth Wheate, and make the Ephah ſmall, and the ſhekell great, and falſifie the weights by deceit?</hi> As wee haue many amongſt vs at this day, that ſpie out their oportunities to raiſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5091:13"/> their prices, as both at ſowing time, full tide, &amp; the latter end of the yere.</p>
            <p>By this means it may be alſo truly ſaid, that the lord hath broaken our ſtaffe of bread, for though heere be corne and graine ſufficient in the land (as I haue prooued) yet the price is inhaunſed ſo high, that the poore ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not attain to it: for how can they when their earnings amount not to aboue foure or fiue ſhillings a weeke for a man, hee hauing ſeauen or eight perſons depending vpon him to bee releeued with the ſame: as for example, I know many poore Miniſters, yea, and ſome of them ſufficient preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who hauing but ten poundes a yeare ſtipend to liue on, who are charged as I haue ſaid, whoſe main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance will not ſuffice to finde him and his breade onelie, after the rate and price that Corne is now come vnto, a pittifull caſe: conſider O King, &amp; let all ſuch hard-hearted Corne-ſellers and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of their bretheren, that either by hardneſſe of heart, couetouſneſſe, or crueltie, tranſportation or conueying away of Corne from their natiue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and neighbours (now in time of dearth &amp; ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie eſpecially) to Aliens, Pyrates, or other nations, and ſee and ſuffer their poore Bretheren and Siſters at home to lye in the Streets, and at their doores, and complaine, and pine and periſh.</p>
            <p>Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſay conſider what the Lord of hoſts ſaith vnto them, verily thus: The Lord hath ſworne by the excellency of <hi>Iacob</hi> and ſaide: <hi>ſurely I will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get any of their workes.</hi> And againe, ſhall not the land tremble for this, and euery one mourne therein? <hi>Amos.</hi> 8. verſe. 4. 5. As if he ſhould ſay to them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5091:13"/> as <hi>Abraham</hi> once ſaid to <hi>Diues. Sonne remember that thou in thy life time liuedſt in pleaſure, and Lazarus in paine, now he is comforted and thou art tormented.</hi> The third and laſt way whereby the Lord is ſaid to break the Staffe of bread, is when the Lord giueth the fruits of the earth in aboundance, and habilitie ſufficient to prouide them, in ſomuch that many eat and drinke thereof continually, and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, they are alwaies empty, hungry and not ſatiſfied. And al becauſe God hath not bleſſed it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, neither they ſhewed themſelues thankfull vnto him therefore: for how many of this ſorte of people may a man finde at this day amongſt vs, that ſit downe and eat and drink and fill themſelues from day today, and riſe vp againe, neuer thanking the lord for his benefits. This point the prophet <hi>Oſe</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, Chap. 4. 10. ſaying, <hi>For they ſhall eat and not haue enough, they ſhal commit adultery and ſhall not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and all becauſe they haue left off to take heed vnto the Lord:</hi> as if he would ſay, to be thankful vnto the Lord for his benefits. Agreeable thereunto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Hagge.</hi> Chap. 1. 4. ſaith alſo; <hi>Ye haue ſowen much and bring in little, ye eat but ye haue not inough, ye drink but ye are not filled, ye cloth you, but ye are not warm, ye earn much, but ye put it in a bottomles bag:</hi> like vnto thoſe that haue the dropſie, who are euer drinking, &amp; are euer dry; or as the couetous, who are alwaies cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and neuer ſatiſfied nor content, and all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord doth not bleſſe it vnto them, not conſidering that the bleſſing of God, maketh rich and bringeth no ſorrowes with it, Pro. 10, 22. It is wonderful to conſider (if many had grace ſo to do)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5091:14"/> how much the bleſſing of God, auaileth in this caſe: For to ſpeake vpon mine owne experience heerein; I haue ſeene where the creatures of God haue bene receiued without reuerence, and giuing of thankes; that as much hath bene weekely douou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in bread onely of two perſons, as where they haue ben taken with ſobriety and thankfulnes, hath ſufficed eight other perſons, yea and thoſe eight in better liking and ſtate, then the other two.</p>
            <p>As we read of <hi>Daniel</hi> and his fellowes, who fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on pulſe, and drinking water, were in better liking then thoſe that had the kings portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I ſpeak it I ſay vppon perfect knowledge and experience. Of which ſort of people, the Poet <hi>Iuuenall</hi> maketh mention, to haue bene in his time, of whome he writeth thus, <hi>Nos numerus ſumus, fruges conſumere na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</hi> meaning, that there were a number borne (as it ſeemed) to no other end but onely to eat, and drink and die. Of whome the Apoſtle ſaint <hi>Paul</hi> maketh mention, ſaying, <hi>For many walke of whome I haue tolde you often, and now tell you weeping, that they are: the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the croſſe of Chriſt, whoſe end is damnation, whoſe belly is their God, whoſe glory is their ſhame, which minde earthly thinges, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence it may appeare, that when the Lord breaketh the ſtaffe of bread, bleſſeth not the labour: where thankſgiuing is not vſed, neither ſobrietie practiſed nor regarded, there is both hunger and famine continually.</p>
            <p>Which may ſerue for an Item, to all Epicures, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, and ſwaggerers, that neither think on God
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5091:14"/> receiuing his benefits, nor thanke him for them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing receiued.</p>
            <p>But me thinkes I heare it demaunded, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth the Lord vſe ſuch darke and figuratiue ſpeeches in deliuering his meſſage vnto his people? partly for the deepe ſenſe and manifold vſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be made, and partly as our ſaniour ſaith, <hi>Mat. 13. 13. To you it is giuen to know the miſteries of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God,</hi> That is, to the prudent, ſtudious, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of wiſedome: for as the greateſt treaſures are commonly found in the deepeſt mines, and the ſweeteſt kirnell within the hardeſt ſhell: ſo the dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker ſpeech, the deeper ſenſe, and the harder words, the higher miſtery: As may appeere by that which heere enſueth.</p>
            <p>For like as a ſtaffe is a ſtrength &amp; ſtay vnto an old, lame, &amp; impotent perſon in his gate, if it be whole and ſound; or as a man that hath a iorney to goe, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a ſtaffe in his hand, aſwell for defence (if any danger hap) as alſo for other neceſſary vſes; which if it be crackt or broken, ſtandeth in no ſteed, but if it be whole, it auaileth much:</p>
            <p>So bread is vnto the body of man a neceſſary ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, to ſupport him in the affaires of this life, ſo long as he can haue it: but if it hap to be ſcanted or with-holden from him, he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not longindure: Both which may teach vs theſe good dueties, Firſt, dayly and dilligently to aske it at the hands of God by prayer, as alſo to returne vnto him due ſacrifice, of praiſe and thankſgiuing therefore: In both which reſpects, no doubt but there are many very negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and remiſſe.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:5091:15"/>
            <p>But howſoeuer, or whenſoeuer it is broken or diminiſhed, we ſee by this, that is heere ſaide, that our ſinnes are the cauſe of it: but for what ſinne or ſinnes? there is the queſtion: for ſome thinke it is for pride, and ſo it may well ſeeme, for was there euer ſuch flaunting in faſhions, or coſt in coloures? ſuch laſing and faſing, cuts or conceites, as are now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies vſed of many, who neuer ſtint cutting of whole cloth into iags and rags, and all for a little paltry pride, and filthy faſhion, moſt contrary vnto Chriſt his coat, which had no ſeame? which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in miſtery doth teach an other thing; yet in plaine words ſhould teach vs to make our gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſomewhat decent, modeſt, and chriſtian-like. Some againe thinke that couetouſnes is the cauſe thereof, aswell it may be ſuppoſed: for was there euer ſuch leaſe-monging, copie catching or running for reuerſions, as is now a daies? for if a man haue but a life or two in his liuing (if it be any thing better then his yearely rent) he ſhal be ſure to haue it taken ouer his head, if he beſtirre not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the better: or if he haue 20. or 30. yeares to come in his leaſe, except he make the better haſte, he is like to come too ſhort of a further eſtate: yea though the yeres current and vnexpired be not like to be ended before the worlde be ended. Some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine thinke whoredome to be the cauſe of this dearth, which indeede ſo ouerfloweth the land as <hi>Noes</hi> flood did ſometime the world.</p>
            <p>Some impute it vnto vſury and extortion, for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was there ſuch vſury I ſuppoſe, for heere is vſe vpon vſe, that is, vſe for the vſe, beſide vſe for the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5091:15"/> principall, notwithmanding that the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> hath ſaid. <hi>Lord who ſhall dwell in thy Tabernacle, or reſt in thy holy hill? Euen he that hath not giuen his mony to vſury, nor taketh reward againſt the innocent.</hi> Pſ. 15. 1. 5. And as for extortion I ſay no more, but let all thoſe that take fees in offices or for office, take heed thereof.</p>
            <p>Others thinke that drunkennes is the cauſe that our Staffe of bread is broken; ſome ſay ſwearing, for neuer was there more of either. Thus <hi>Quot ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines tot ſententiae</hi> (as they ſay) ſo many men, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mindes. But if I might enterpoſe my Iudgement among the reſt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the very efficient, &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue cauſe indeed of this breaking the Staffe of bread amongſt vs; I would ſay with <hi>Salomon, In quo quis peccat, in eo punietur,</hi> that is, wherin a man offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth or ſinneth, therein or thereafter, he ſhalbe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. Sap. 11. 13. whereunto <hi>Moſes</hi> aſtipulateth, ſaying: <hi>Pro menſura peccati, erit plaga,</hi> that is, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of the treſpas, or hurt, the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ſhall be. Deu. 25. 2. Now, if the equitie both of deuine and humane lawes be ſuch, that wherein a man ſinneth or treſpaſſeth, therin or ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, he ſhalbe puniſhed; then although the leaſt of thoſe ſinnes before recited, haue deſerued to haue our Staffe of bread broken: yet more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to define thereof, I may ſay, that as the Lord hath three manner of waies broken our ſtaffe of bread, ſo there may be gathered three ſpeciall cauſes, more iuſtly procuring the ſame then the reſt.</p>
            <p>Like as we read that the ſinnes of <hi>Sodome</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5091:16"/> 
               <hi>Gomore,</hi> were pride, fulnes of bread, that is, glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and drunkennes, aboundance of idlenes, and not ſtrengthning the hand of the poore; yet when we rightly conſider of their puniſhment, we ſhall finde that as they burned in vnlawfull luſt one towards an other, ſo were they burned and conſumed with fire and brimſtone from heauen: like as our late Arch-traytors, that intended to blow vp others with Gunne-pouder, were ſome of them ſtroke downe with the ſame, and others ſo ſcorched, that they carried it to their graues, So righteous is God in all his waies, and holy in all his workes.</p>
            <p>Thus in like manner may we ſuppoſe, that of this threefold breaking our ſtaffe of bread, there may be gathered three capitall crimes, or principall cauſes aboue the reſt. As firſt, our great contempt of the heauenly <hi>Manna,</hi> and ſweete foode of our ſoules; our diſobedience to the word of God, I meane, ſo plentifully and purely preached amongſt vs. And this dooth DAVID moſt plainely prooue in the pſ. 81. verſe 13. whereas he ſaith: <hi>O that my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would haue hearkened vnto me,</hi> That is, vnto my word preached amongſt them; <hi>and Iſraell had wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in my waies!</hi> Marke the anſwere, verſe 16. <hi>Then would I haue fed them with the fat of wheat, and with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, out of the rocke would I haue ſufficed thee.</hi> As if he would haue ſaide, becauſe ye haue not hearkened to my word, nor obeyed the ſame, I haue ſcanted your bread and broken the ſtaffe thereof. But heere haply you will ſay, of what manner of perſons is the word of God ſo deſpiſed, as you ſpeake of? Firſt, of the Recuſant Papiſts, that will not heare it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5091:16"/> read nor preached, except it be ofa Maſſe prieſt, and that in the latine tongue. Secondly, of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſian, that cares not to heare it read in the church at all, nor preached, except it be of ſuch a miniſter as doth refuſe ſubſcription. Yea but thoſe are eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and taken for the moſt zealous profeſſours of al: They would indeed be ſo accounted, but I finde by experience, that they haue done more harme in the Church, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer the Recuſant papiſts did, that would not come to church at all For heereby the miniſtery is reproached, the word deſpiſed, and the people ſo deſtracted, that wheras before they were very attentiue to the word read and preached, and duely reſorted to their ſeuerall pariſhes; now they runne ſome one way and ſome another, as it were ſo many ſheep without a Shepheard, not ſuffering wholeſome doctrine, but hauing their eares it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, do after their owne luſts, get them an heape of teachers, euen as S. <hi>Paul</hi> long ſince propheſied, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. verſe 3.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt ſort of them that contemne the word, are thoſe, old and cold proteſtants that do v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually and daily come and ſit before the miniſter &amp; heare but how? none otherwiſe then thoſe Iſralites of whome the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> maketh mention, ſaying, <hi>For they come to thee, as the people vſe to come, &amp; my people ſit before thee, and heare thy words, but they will not doe them, for with their mouthes they make iestes, and their heart goeth after their couetouſnes: and loe, thou art vnto them as a ieſting ſong of one that hath a pleaſant voyce, and can ſing well, for they heard thy words, but they do them not.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:5091:17"/>
            <p>And thus is the word of God contemned in a manner of all, or at the leaſt of the greateſt part of the people amongſt vs.</p>
            <p>The ſecond cauſe of this our ſtaffe of breade bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, is, (as I take it) the corrupting or abuſing of thoſe good creatures of Wheate and Barlye, which God ſo plentifully hath heretofore powred downe vpon vs, as for many yeares paſt they haue bin. But happily you wil ſay, wherin or how haue we abuſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Behold, &amp; I wil ſhew you: Firſt, of wheat, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Lord hath made as a ſure promiſe to feede vs with the fineſt Flower therof: haue not we turned it from the right vſe thereof, in filling our bellyes, vnto the fineing of our necks, by cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging it from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of bread into making of ſtarch? a moſt vile and abhominable abuſe, when you ſhall haue in ſome one little town in this Land as much wheat week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpent in making of Starch as in making of bread: and as for the other graine of Barlie, who knowes not how many waies it is, and hath bin miſpent of many: ſome feeding their Hogs, ſome their Dogs and Horſes therewith, where as Chriſt himſelfe was content to feede himſelfe therewith, &amp; feaſted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands. Others conuerting it into mault in ſuch exceſſiue manner and meaſure, as paſſeth to ſpeake of, &amp; then tranſporting it who knowes whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? that both the price is enhaunſed therby as you ſee, &amp; dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kennes dayly maintained: for what is it to haue an hundred buſhels of Mault brewed in one little Towne euerie weeke in the yeare, where as twentie would ſuffice? One of the ſinnes of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> was (as you haue heard) fulneſſe of bread, ſo I
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5091:17"/> may ſay, that one of the chiefe ſinnes of this land is fulneſſe of drinke, and ſurely not the leaſt, nor in the laſt place of thoſe which haue cauſed this our Staffe of breade to be broaken. For if a man do but note the abhominable quaffing and carowſing, with kneeling on their knees to their God <hi>Bacchus</hi> (I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) as it is vſed in many places, in taking of their liquor, it would make any Chriſtian heart to ake to beholde or heare thereof.</p>
            <p>This I ſay, I take to be not onely the cauſe or one of the cauſes why the ſtaffe of our corporall foode is broken; but alſo of our Spirituall in ſo many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſcanted, through the ſtrength of many, who are ſtrong to ſet vp drunkenneſſe, as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> writeth. Capter. 5. who ſhould bee rather dealing and diſtributing of that liquor, of the which if a man once taſte or drinke of, hee ſhall neuer more be a thirſt, as our ſauiour ſhoweth, Io. 4. 14. This is it that the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> meant, ſaying: Chapter. 8. 11. <hi>Beholde, the daies come ſaith the Lord, that I will bring a Famine in the land, not a Famine of Breade, nor a thirſt of water, but of hearing the word of the Lord.</hi> Which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine euen in theſe our daies of dearth &amp; ſcarſitie, hath not bene a little threatned, and which thirſt is te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thouſand times worſe then the former. For this is the famine of the ſoule, and the ſpirituall drought that the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpeaketh of Chap. 50. ver. 38 ſaying: <hi>Siccit as ſuper aquas. A drought is vpon his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and they ſhall be dryed vp. &amp;c.</hi> For by how much the ſoule is more precious then the body, by ſo much the more is the death or famine of it to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, then of the other.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:5091:18"/>
            <p>But heere it may bee demaunded whether that the ſame bee the cauſes of the one as the other? no, for as the thinges be different, ſo the cauſes are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie, &amp; yet being conſidered in a ſpirituall thought, we ſhall finde them verie correſpondent the one to the other. For as diſobedience, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, &amp; vnthankfulneſſe are the cauſes of the one, ſo reiecting &amp; neglecting are the cauſes of the other.</p>
            <p>Euen as the Iſraelites when they were cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Manna, murmured, and had Quailes; ſo manye amongſt vs at this day, beeing drunken with ſuperfluitie (but not of Wine) haue ſpewed vp againe that which was good at the firſt receauing, and haue longed for that which was worſe, as the Iſraelites did for the fleſh-pots of Egipt.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the third cauſe which I haue aſſigned to vnthankfulneſſe; for as much as the Lord in a maner looketh for nothing elſe at our hands, for all the benefits that hee hath giuen vs, appeareth by <hi>Dauid.</hi> Pſalm. 116. verſe, 12. 17. where he ſaith, <hi>What ſhall I giue or render vnto the Lord for all his benefits towards mee?</hi> The anſwere is, <hi>I will offer to thee a ſacrifice of praiſe, and will call vpon the name of the Lord:</hi> as if he would ſay, <hi>I will giue him thankes, and praiſe his name.</hi> And againe, Pſame. 63. verſ. 5. 6. <hi>As long as I liue I will magnifie thee on this manner, and will lift vp my hands in thy name: my ſoule ſhall bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied euen as it were with marrowe and fatneſſe, when my mouth prayſeth thee with ioyfull lippes.</hi> Yet our mouthes cannot ſo doe, becauſe they are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe filled with Oathes, Curſſes, Blaſphemies, and other prophanes, or elſe vtterlye mute and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5091:18"/> ſilent, as I haue ſhewed.</p>
            <p>Thus much concerning the cauſes both origni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and accidentall of Dearth, the Metaphores, or phraſe of ſpeech, the ſenſe and meaning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and the Miſteries and Doctrines therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. And ſo now I come to the effects and fruits thereof. <hi>(And I will ſend Famine vpon it)</hi> this Famine as you haue heard is to bee taken two manner of waies; that is, eyther for the defect of Spirituall or of Corporall foode. Concerning the firſt, which I holde moſte proper vnto this place, the whole ſcriptures are pregnant, ſhewing how God, not onely threatned, but alſo brought the ſame to paſſe in all ages, puniſhing ſometimes therewith ſome particular places and perſons: ſometimes whole Nations, and ſometimes the whole world, as wee read in Ge. Ch: 12. 26. 41. &amp; 47. How the Lord viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the South in the daies of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iacob:</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt in the daies of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> Samaria &amp; Ieruſalem &amp; other Nations from time to time.</p>
            <p>The prophets <hi>Eſay, Ieremie,</hi> and <hi>Ezechiel</hi> in one and the ſelfe ſame Chap, viz. the 14. (as if they had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken al three with one mouth, as they did by one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) doe ſhew that the Lord will kil the root of <hi>Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina,</hi> and not leaue the rebellions of Iuda &amp; Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, vnpuniſhed with famine. How iuſt &amp; true the Lord is in al his promiſes &amp; propheſeings, our own experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce can beſt of all bear witnes, who haue taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the twigs of this rod three ſeuerall times within the ſpace of twentie foure yeres, wherein we haue or might haue heard and ſeene the poore, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablye crying, and dying through the extreami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5091:19"/> of dearth and famine. Oh! but happilye you will ſay, I neuer heard or ſaw any ſuch. <hi>Anſ.</hi> But I haue, who am both <hi>auritus</hi> and <hi>oculatus teſtis:</hi> that is, both an eare and an eye witneſſe thereof.</p>
            <p>Indeed I think that many of ſuperiour place haue not ſeene ſo much: for as the common ſaying is, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quila non capit muſcas,</hi> the Eagle taketh no Flies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee ſoareth ſo hye. And ſo doe many of the richer ſort of this world, ſildome or neuer beholde nor heare, or thoroughlye feele and vnderſtand the State of the poore diſtreſſed: As Diues little felt what were <hi>Lazarus</hi> paines or hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. But in as much as the Lord hath ſaid <hi>he wil ſend famine vpon the land that committeth a trepaſſe against him,</hi> let that bee one proofe. Like as that wofull fact of that Woman in Samaria, that ſodde her Sonne one day, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to the King that her Neighbour would not doe the like for her next day.</p>
            <p>But heere it may be demaunded vnto what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſons this dearth of ours is a Plague, or a famine? <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not vnto the rich I ſuppoſe, for they feele it not, no more then <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did the dearth in Egipt, and therefore it may well be called the poore mans plague, for ſo it is: But what? you wil then ſay haue not the rich ſinned as well as the poore? yes. And haue not they procured this plague as wel as the poore? yes. Why then are not they puniſhed as the reſt? My cenſure you ſhall ſee.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay with the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> that iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment beginneth at the houſe of God. Secondly like as <hi>Pharao</hi> felt not the ſtroake of dearth in Egipt, nor his iolly courtiers about him, yet you ſee how after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5091:19"/> hee and they were all deſtroyed in the red ſea. So when God hath viſited the poore (which are his owne houſe) hee will come vppon the mighty with greater iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts afterwards: for as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>the mighty ſhal be mightily tormented,</hi> Sap. 6. 6. And <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſaith: <hi>He will not verily cleere the wicked.</hi> It follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. <hi>And I wil deſtroy both man and beaſt forth of it:</hi> Such is the iealouſie and wrath of Almightie God, that when ſinners will not repent, he not onely doth pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh their ſinnes to the third and fourth generation; but alſo extendeth the ſame, aſwell vnto the vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creatures, ſuch as the Beaſts and Birdes are, as vnto the vnſenſible earth and fruites thereof, by making it either as hard as yron vnder foote, or elſe the Heauen as braſſe ouer head. q. d. Both ſhall bee vnfruitefull and vnſeaſonable; ſo that by their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperature, the Beaſtes or Cattel ſhall likewiſe be deſtroyed, As for example, what murrens of Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, and rots of Sheepe haue wee had in this Land, within the ſpace of theſe fewe yeares paſt? And as for the perſons that dyed that way, who can tell the number or names of them? And ſo I come to the third and laſt part of this Text, wherein are ſet downe the helpes and remedies of this dearth now beeing, if they may be effectually put in practiſe. It followes: <hi>Though theſe three men,</hi> Noe, Daniel <hi>and</hi> Iob <hi>were amongst them, they ſhall deliuer but their owne ſoules by their Righteouſnes, ſaith the Lord:</hi> But mee thinkes I heare ſome ſay, what helpes or remedies are to be found or gathered from theſe wordes? or what point of doctrine or knowledge is heere to be had concerning the ſame?</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:5091:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Surely all that euer the word of God teacheth to be done in ſuch a caſe; and that is enough and ſufficient, if wee had eyes to ſee, or hearts to vnderſtand. But in as much as many haue eies and ſee not, and hearts and vnderſtand not, (for the natural man perceiueth not the things that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the ſpirit of God) for how can he, ſeeing that they are ſpiritually diſcerned? Therfore haue I thought good at this time to lay ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more at large the ſence, Doctrin, &amp; vſes of this Scripture. But firſt let vs conſider what coherence or reference, it may haue with other places of like nature: for in <hi>Ieremy</hi> the 15. Chap. v. 1. it is ſaide vpon like occaſion, <hi>Though Moſes &amp; Samuel stood before me, yet mine affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could not bee toward this people.</hi> The ſence or mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of both which places is thus: that there is no entreatie with the Lord for the wicked and vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant people of the world: But in no caſe anye preiudice vnto the faithfull flocke of Ieſus Chriſt. For, as we may ſee how abſolutely the Lord refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to heare <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> praying for them, yet it ſhutteth not the dore of repentance to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and penitent, as we finde in verſe 15. &amp; 19. where the Lord both promiſeth vnto <hi>Ieremy,</hi> that if hee would returne vnto him, and the people with him, they ſhould bee brought againe, and ſtand before the Lord.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Ieremy</hi> for his owne part (notwithſtanding the former communication) prayeth ſaying: <hi>O Lord, thou knoweſt, remember mee, and viſite, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge mee of my perſecutors, take mee not away in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of thy wrath, &amp;c.</hi> Euen as in this place it is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5091:20"/> ſaide, though <hi>Noe, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> were amongſt them, &amp;c. where againe we learne, that as there is no place nor reaſon of reconciliation, left vnto the wicked, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing in their wickednes, yet the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and repentant (how few ſoeuer they be) haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies free acceſſe vnto the throane of grace, ſo oft as they ſhal return vnto the Lord their God, which maketh much for the conſolation of the godly, as on the contrary part, it may increaſe the terrour &amp; trouble of the wicked, more and more: which doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> maketh plaine, pſ. 32. 10. ſaying; <hi>Many ſorrowes ſhall come to the wicked, but he that truſteth in the Lord, mercy ſhall imbrace him on euery ſide.</hi> A moſt euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t example we haue of this, in the deſtruction of <hi>Core, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> with their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany: &amp; the deliuerance of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> with their partakers, notwithſtanding there was offring of Incenſe on both ſides, yea, and that at one &amp; the ſelfe ſame time, yet the rebellious part onely peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and the obedient were preſerued and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>Againe, when the plague was begunne, and the wrath of the Lord gone foorth, for the murmuring of thoſe that eſcaped the ſwallowing of <hi>Corah</hi> (as were read in the ſame chapter, v. 14. ſo that there died 14. thouſand and ſeauen hundered in a ſhort time, and the Lord had ſaide, that he would deſtroy euen the whole congregation; yet when <hi>Aaron</hi> at the commaund of <hi>Moſes,</hi> had taken a Cenſer, &amp; put fire therein of the Altar, with Incenſe, and made the attonement, hee ſtanding betweene the dead and the liuing, the plague ceaſed.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:5091:21"/>
            <p>A ſinguler document for vs at this day, who ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the like predicament of puniſhment of (for as they were puniſhed with the plague of peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilence, for their rebellions againſt the miniſters of God, enen ſo we for our rebellions againſt the word of God with dearth and Famine) and therfore had neede to take our Cenſers, that is, our hearts, and put fire therein, (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith in the perſon of VViſdome) <hi>My Sonne giue mee thy heart,,</hi> and put therein the fire and zeale, that wee may bee feruent in Prayer, and call vpon the name of the Lord ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlye, as our high Prieſt Ieſus Chriſt hath taught by his owne example; who in his Agonie, when the hand of the Lord was vpon him, as wee reade in S. Luke, chap. 22. verſe. 44. prayed moſt inſtantly. This is the verie doctrine of this place, for what doth the prophet elſe mean, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith: <hi>Though</hi> Noe, Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el <hi>&amp;</hi> Iob, <hi>that were amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gst the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> but this, that ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as theſe were, who called vpon the name of the lord in their troubles, as <hi>Daniel</hi> preached his word faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully as <hi>Noe,</hi> and practiſed the ſame effectually in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſations, as <hi>Iob</hi> did, ſhal deliuer their own ſoules by their righteouſnes, that is, ſuch as repent them truely of their ſinnes, and put their truſt in the Lord, euen as <hi>Salomon</hi> likewiſe teacheth ſaying: When there ſhal be famine in the land: when there ſhall be peſtilence, blaſting, or Mildew, Groſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or caterpiller, when the enemie ſhall beſeidge them in the cittie of the Land, or any plague, or any ſickneſſe. Then what prayer or ſupplication ſoeuer ſhall be made of any man, or of al thy people Iſrael, when euerie one ſhal knowe his owne Plague, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5091:21"/> his own diſeaſe, &amp; ſhal ſtretch forth his hands tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards this houſe, meaning the Temple: Heare thou then in heauen thy dwelling place, and be merciful and giue euerie man according to his waies, as thou dooſt knowe his heart, for thou onely knoweſt the hearts of the Children of men. Thus doth <hi>Salomon</hi> (like as <hi>Moſes)</hi> teach, how in al our troubles and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, we muſt take the cenſure of a troubled and ſanctified ſoule, and come to the Lord his Temple, whereſoeuer two or three ſhall bee gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and make our praiers and ſupplications, knowing &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging our plague, and our diſeaſe, that is, our own fin, &amp; ſhal ſtretch forth our hands towards the new Ieruſalem: that then God will heare in heauen his dwelling place, and be mercifull, &amp; giue euery one according to his waies. Therefore ſhall euerie one that is Godly ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſalm. 32. 6. make his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vnto thee in time, when thou maiſt be found. And therefore are theſe Patriarkes and Prophets heere named, <hi>Noe, Daniel</hi> and <hi>Iob,</hi> who all of them called vpon the Lord in their neceſſities, and were holpen as we read in Gen. 7. Dan. 6. Iob. 39. chapters. For heere by prayer-making or calling on the Lord, is ment the whole worſhip of God, a part put for the whole, as likewiſe our Sauiour teacheth in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ſaying: <hi>Come vnto me all ye that are wearie and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and I wil eaſe you,</hi> where by comming vnto me, Chriſt teacheth what hee would haue vs to doe, namely: Firſt to beleeue in him, to heare his word, to receiue his Sacraments, to ſanctifie his Saboaths and powre foorth our hearts before him, in all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5091:22"/> of praier, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion, thanks-giuing, &amp; ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as we learn in 1. <hi>Tim. 2. 1.</hi> Therfore doth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet heere ſay; <hi>Though</hi> Noe, Daniel, <hi>and</hi> Iob <hi>were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them;</hi> ſignifying heereby, how ſmall the number of true conuerts ſhould bee in all ages. Likewiſe <hi>Noe</hi> before the Law, amongſt the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes, as <hi>Daniel</hi> vnder the Lawe amongſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and <hi>Iob</hi> without the Lawe amongſt the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</p>
            <p>Againe, like as <hi>Noe</hi> ſignifieth reſt, ſo there ſhould be few at al times in the Church that ſhould bee at reſt or peace with God, through a true and liuelye faith in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſignifieth iudgement of the Lord, ſo there ſhould be fewe that vnderſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right his iudgements. And as <hi>Iob</hi> ſignifieth ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſo there ſhould be few truely ſorrowfull or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent for their ſinnes, as by perfect experience wee prooue it in theſe daies; for notwithſtanding the Goſpell hath long time ſhined amongſt vs; and the iudgements of God haue bene plentifully powred down vpon vs, both by ſea &amp; land, by Fire &amp; water, Plague and Peſtilence, Dearth and Famine, &amp;c. yet where is one <hi>Noe</hi> or preacher of righteouſnes, that buildeth vp the Arke (as God bad him) as he did? or where is one <hi>Daniel</hi> that refuſeth the Kings portion, and prouiſion; that is, any pleaſure or profit of this life, and contents himſelfe with pulſe and water, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing himſelfe to prayer and faſting, as <hi>Daniel</hi> did? or where is one <hi>Iob</hi> to be found ſo patient and peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that of whome it may bee ſaide, as it was of him in all his afflictions, that in all this hee ſinned
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5091:22"/> not, neither charged God fooliſhly: for theſe be the verie true helps &amp; meanes to redreſſe this dearth &amp; Famine, if it wold pleaſe God to giue vs ſuch grace.</p>
            <p>The Lord be mercifull vnto vs, and create in vs new hearts, and right ſpirits, that wee may in due time breake off our ſinnes by repentance, and turne to the Lord our God with all our heartes vnfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(Were amongst them)</hi> q. d. either to preach to them as <hi>Noe</hi> did to the olde world, or to pray for them, as <hi>Daniel</hi> did for the Iſraelites in Captiuitie, or to giue example of holy life, as <hi>Iob</hi> did of all long ſuffering, patience, and repentance, which are the verie true meanes and remedies of theſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God now inflicted vpon vs, as I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> prooueth moſte plainelye in the 67. Pſalme ſaying: <hi>Let the people praiſe thee O God, yea, let all the people praiſe thee, Then ſhall the Earth bring foorth her encreaſe, and God, euen our own God ſhall giue vs his bleſsing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where vnder the word <hi>(Praiſe)</hi> are contained all the dueties of our deuotion towards God, as Faith, Prayer, Preaching, Repentance, holy life, &amp;c. But happilye heere ſome will ſay, haue not wee manye Godlye Preachers, deuout Orators, and diuine liuers amongſt vs at this day as euer were? as <hi>Daniel</hi> was then liuing amongſt the Iewes, as likewiſe this prophet <hi>Ezechel,</hi> a man of God, &amp;c True it is, that both <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Ezechiel</hi> were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, &amp; amongſt the Iewes, as it is to be hoped that there are many of the Seruants of God amongſt vs at this day, both Prophets and Paſtors, and yet by reaſon of the captiuitie that they were in, and the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5091:23"/> peoples Idolatrie which they had ſette vp in their hearts, (as this Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſheweth in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this 14. Ch. how they had done, ſaying: <hi>Son of man, theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſet vp their Idols in their harts, and put the ſtumbling blocke of their iniquities before their face, ſhould I being required anſwere them?</hi> I ſay, what by reaſon of the peoples Idolatrie, and their capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie and hard entreaty, they were neither regarded nor beleeued. As many of the ſeruants of God amongſt vs at this day are in like maner dealt with: from whence may be gathered, that the people doe not make that vſe of Gods ſeruants, whether abſent or preſent amongſt them, as they ought to do: God graunt this ſinne be not amongſt vs, but it is greatly to be feared that it is, for where is one <hi>Zaccheus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the rich that ſtandeth forth, and ſaith in this needefull time of comfort, <hi>Beholde Lord, the halfe of my goods I giue to the poore, &amp;c.</hi> or where is their one <hi>Lidies</hi> heart ſo opened, that doth cheerfully receiue or charitably refreſh the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God as ſhe did? I ſay, where is there one Man or one Woman ſo wonne by the word that layeth a part one linke of his Golden chaine, one lace of her veluet fleeue, or a bateth one breadth of their broade ruffes, or ſetteth a part one diſh of their dainty ſuperfluities at euery feaſt, towards the releefe of ſo many poore Lazares as abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d round about vs at this day? yea, what haue I ſeene to the contrarie? namely thus: that where there hath bene a motion made on the Saboath day in the Church by the miniſter to the whole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation aſſembled in the behalfe of two poore, ſicke, naked, hungrie, and impotent perſons for ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe; there hath bene gathered in the ſame day, in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5091:23"/> the afternoone, foure times as much for a Beare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and his beare, as hath bene giuen and collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted towardes thoſe two poore Chriſtian perſons, which argueth the coldneſſe of charitie in manye hearts, and the deadnes of deuotion amongſt thoſe that ſhould ſhine as Lampes in all manner of good workes aboue others. So that of the true zealous: deuout and charitable conuerted Chriſtian indeed, I may ſay as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh of the good interpreter; if there bee one amongſt a thouſand it is maruaile: wherefore, in the way of a general Admonition, I ſay, let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leaſt he fall, for but onely <hi>Noe, Daniell,</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their owneſoules by their righteouſnes, that is, from the plague or puniſhment that I wil bring vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, from whence ariſeth a double queſtion to be diſſolued.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whether any man can deliuer his own ſoule by his righteouſnes? Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, whether there be any ſuch righteouſnes in man, as that thereby he ſhould deliuer his owne ſoule, or the ſoule of another man from any preſent plague or puniſhment, or from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting death, as ſome ſuppoſe? To the firſt I anſwere, that no man can deliuer his ſoule, nor the ſoule of another man from death temporall, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, which the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> prooueth plainly ſaying: <hi>Yet a man by no meanes can redeeme his brother, he cannot giue his ranſome to God, ſo precious is the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſoules &amp; the continuance for euer, that he may liue ſtil for euer, &amp; not ſee the graue.</hi> Pſ. 49. ver. 7. 8. 9. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to approue that there is no ſuch righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in man, as therby to deliuer his owne Soule, the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5091:24"/> prophet Dauid ſaith plainelye, Pſalme 143. 2. <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not in iudgement with thy Seruant O Lord, for no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fleſh is righteous in thy ſight.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> Chap. 64. verſe 6. ſaith, <hi>But we haue bene all as an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thing, and all our righteouſneſse is as filthy cloutes.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo teacheth, that not by the workes of righteouſneſſe which wee haue wrought, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his mercie hee ſaued vs, by the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the newe birth, and renewing of the holye Ghoſt. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 5. But then you will ſay, how dooth the Prophet heere ſay, that they ſhould deliuer but their owne ſoules by their righteouſneſſe? that is, as I haue ſhewed already; from ſome temporall plague or puniſhment threatned or deſerued. As wee reade of the King of <hi>Niniute</hi> and his people, how they preuented their deſtruction by repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which otherwiſe ſhould haue enſued within fortye daies. Of <hi>Hezekia,</hi> who calling vppon the Lord in the time of his ſickenes, and truely repenting, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed his daies for 15: yeres afterward, &amp; ſo exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples might be giuen of many others.</p>
            <p>Againe, it may bee anſwered, that <hi>Soule</hi> in this place is taken for the life of man, as <hi>Ionas</hi> delareth the like. Io. 4. 3. ſaying. <hi>And now O Lord, I beſeech thee to take away my life, for it is better for me to die then liue.</hi> Where the Latine word which is put for life is <hi>Anima,</hi> which ſignifieth the ſoule, ſo that the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of any man, that is, his perfection, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe, or holineſſe of life, is but to deliuer him from ſome temporall Plague or puniſhment, and not that neither, except hee require and ſeeke it at the handes of God, in and by the righteouſneſſe, merits, and Mediation of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:5091:24"/>
            <p>By whome as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Col. 4. 13: I am able to doe all thinges by the helpe of Chriſt, who ſtrengthneth me, and without whome we are able to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> as himſelfe teacheth. Ion. 15. verſ. 5. ſaying: <hi>Sine me poteſt is nihil. Without mee yee can doe nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But dooth not this gaine ſay the opinion of our aduerſaries the Papiſts, both for Inuocation &amp; Saints, and for merrit of workes? let it be well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered that followeth, and ye ſhall ſee, The words that followe are theſe, <hi>(Saith the Lord)</hi> which words are added for a confirmation of the former Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine in mine opinion, as if the holy Ghoſt had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene, (as no doubt but he did) how much heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after it would bee impugned, as wee ſee how it is come to paſſe at this day, amongſt our aduerſaries the Papiſts, who relye much vpon the helps and audience of perſons departed this life; and alſo teach and holde both the merrit of the perſon, and of the worke, affirming that there is ſuch a dignitie in the perſon, that Infants dying immediatelye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Baptiſme, are worthy of eternall life; becauſe although they want good workes, yet are not voide of this kinde of merrit. And for the merrit of workes, they ſay there is ſuch a dignitie or excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie in the work, wherby it is made fit &amp; enabled to deſerue euerlaſting life for the dooer. For works (as they holde) are meritorious two waies. Firſt by couenant, becauſe God hath made a promiſe of reward to them. Secondly, by their owne digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for Chriſt hath merited that they ſhould merit, (as they ſay) both which pointes are ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by this our Text, wherein the prophet ſaith:</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:5091:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Though theſe three men,</hi> Noe, Daniel <hi>and</hi> Iob, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which were as holy, worthy and excellent as euer were any, yet they ſhal deliuer but their own ſoules by their owne righteouſneſſe: By which falleth to ground all merrit of workes, as well of <hi>congruo</hi> and <hi>condigno,</hi> as of <hi>ſupererogation,</hi> &amp; that becauſe partlye as our text ſaith, <hi>They ſhall deliuer but their own ſoules,</hi> as alſo becauſe no fleſh is righteous in his ſight: whereby, neither Infants, how young ſoeuer they die, (who are defiled in the wombe) and elders who liue they neuer ſo long, yet cannot boaſt of one daies cleaneneſſe, nor iuſtly ſay, my heart is pure; &amp; further, becauſe all our dignitie, excellencie and righteouſnes is non otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a defiled cloath: finally, if any man would builde vp inuocation of Saints heeron, beſides, the verie expreſſe words of our Text, the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> will tell vs, that there is but one mediator betweene God and man, euen Ieſus Chriſt, who gaue himſelfe a ranſome for al men, to be a teſtimonie in due time, 1. Tim. 2. 5. 6. And ſo as God, which is the God of al trueth, hath ſpoken and ſaid, Though <hi>Noe, Daniel</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, yet they ſhall deliuer but their owne ſoules by their righteouſneſſe: which may teach vs not to build our ſaluation vpon any mans holines, guifts, or perfection, but rather euerie man to looke vnto God, and to the doctrine of his holy word, which teacheth firſt that the iuſt ſhall liue by faith: and ſecondly that he will reward euerie man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his workes, that is, to them which by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in well dooing ſeeke glorie and honor, and immortallitie, eternall life: but vnto them that are
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5091:25"/> contentious, and diſobey the truth, and obey vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, ſhall be indignation and wrath.</p>
            <p>Therefore let no man ſo deuote himſelfe vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, though they ſeeme as holy, iuſt, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous as <hi>Noe, Dantel</hi> and <hi>Iob,</hi> that in reſpect of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, him or them; they contemne all others. A common fault in theſe daies. God for his mercies ſake giue vs eies to ſee, and hearts to vnderſtand, the holy miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his ſacred word, that we be not onely hearers of the ſame, but doers alſo. And for ſo much as by our ſins, we haue cauſed thy iudgements of dearth and famine (with the reſt) to be powred vpon vs, giue vs O Lord a true touch and feeling thereof in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in our hearts, that wee dally no longer with our ſelues in our ſinnes, and abuſe of thy good crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but rather conſider with our ſelues how farre and how much we haue thereby prouoked thy wrath: remembring alſo that for eating one peece of an Apple, thou expelledſt <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradice; &amp; for one lye thou deſtroyedſt <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Zaphira:</hi> And for gathering of a few ſtickes on the Saboath day, thou cauſedſt that Iſraelite to bee ſtoned. But our ſinnes againſt thee committed haue not bene by one and by one, but by Millions and Thouſands, ſo that if we ſhould take vpon vs to number them, wee know not where to begin, nor how to make an end. And yet thou continueſt holy, &amp; ſendeſt foorth the light of thy word, and the found of thy Trumpet to awake and raiſe vs vp, and to guide our feet into the way of peace. O Lord make vs wiſe vnto the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen &amp; that we may no longer relye vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our owne wits, workes or wiſdome, which is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5091:26"/> carnal, ſenſual, and diueliſh: but teach vs how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer our owne ſoules by our righteouſneſſe, that thou maiſt deliuer both our ſoules and bodies from all euill, both heere in the kingdome of grace, and there heereafter in the kingdome of glorie: that we thy Church militant may be like thy Church Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, and that by the merits and mediation of Ieſus Chriſt onely, in whome are all thy promiſes, both yea and Amen. Vnto which Ieſus Chriſt, with thee O father and the holy Ghoſt, our comforter, three perſons in one eternall and bleſſed deitie be giuen all praiſe, power, glorie and benediction both now and for euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="proverb">
            <pb facs="tcp:5091:26"/>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>A prouerbe pronounced to all the cruell,</hi> couetous, and hard hearted Corne-maiſters, Cloath-maiſters, and al other olde Pinching penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers at this day amongſt vs, who eſteem more of their vnrighteous Mammon then of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Chriſt our bleſſed Sauiour, who aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſeth them to make them friends therof in due time, that they might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into euerlaſting ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles and yet will not.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much as it is ſaide by Chriſt our Sauiour, in his holy Goſpell, that it is eaſier for a Camell to goe through the eye of a needle, then for a rich man to enter into the kingdome of GOD, And againe, in the ſelfe ſame place, <hi>That it is hard for a rich man to enter into the kingdome of heauen.</hi> I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile that the rich men of theſe our daies do no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter looke vnto it, then many of them doe, eſpeciallye ſuch as hauing the ſubſtance of this world in ſuch ſuperfluitie and aboundance as they haue: for was it not vppon great reaſon that our Sauiour did ſo ſay, ſeeing that the deſire of money is the root of all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and they that will be rich fall into te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5091:27"/> and ſnares, and into manye fooliſh and noyſome luſts, which drown me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in perdition &amp; deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as we may eaſily ſee &amp; perceiue both by the manifolde vanities they doe embrace and maintaine, as alſo by the ſundrie wickedneſſes and corruptions they doe commit through the power and ſtrength, I would ſay, the vaine hope &amp; confidence they haue in their wealth: ſome building Babel or Towers of confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſome heaping vp Mydaes mountaines, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell who ſhall inherit or diſpend them: Some as <hi>Diues</hi> in vanities of apparell, ſome in ſuperfluitie of meats wines, drinks: &amp;c ſome in hawking, hunting, Cock-fighting, Beare-bayting, Dycing, dauncing: and others in Tobacco taking, diſpending their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes, or the greateſt part thereof, (for what is it to ſee a yong man of twentie foure yeres, healthy in body, ſound in conſtitution, to diſpend an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred markes <hi>per annum</hi> in Tobacco, when as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Grandfather &amp; whole generation before him, happilye neuer in all their time ſpent one farthing that way? What a vanitie is it then for a man to ſpend ſo much that way, without the which hee may liue wel enough? Beſides, if a man ſhould rip vp the treacheries and treaſons that haue beene from time to time complotted amongſt the richer ſort, we ſhall finde it moſte true that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith. <hi>Pro. 10 16. The labour of the righteous tendeth to life, but the reuenues of the wicked to ſin,</hi> As if hee would ſay more plainly, the wicked ſpend al their lands, rents, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues &amp; liuings, for the moſt part in euil &amp; vngodly waies. 1. In one kinde of vanity or other, ſuch as I haue ſhewed, which how true it falleth out in theſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5091:27"/> daies, who ſeeth not? Amongſt all which wickedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, vanities, or ſinnes, there is not a greater in mine opinion, then this that is heere mentioned in this ſentence following. <hi>Him that with draweth the Corne the people wil curſse, &amp;c.</hi> For how be it that other vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and corruptions doe bring deſtruction to the dooers thereof, and to ſome few of their poſteritie This reacheth further euen to the whole multitude or number of the poore, which is ſo infinite, that it cannot eaſily be numbred. And by how much the more any euil ſparſeth it ſelfe abroad, or groweth more generall, by ſo much the more it is reprooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and to be condemned.</p>
            <p>Then high time it is for the greate ones of this world, the greate rich <hi>Diueſes</hi> I meane, that ſpend ſo manye poundes and pence in meere vanities, in effecting or bringing to paſſe ſo many great &amp; gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous corruptions, (as many of them do) to looke &amp; conſider with themſelues in time, what will bee the end of all this? verilye none other then what is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in this prouerb &amp; ſentence of <hi>Salomon</hi> heere following. Firſt, that they ſhall but gaine the curſe of the people; Secondly of God: for the preuenting and auoiding of both which, I haue thought good to giue this admonition to all that haue their eyes open, I meane any ſparke of grace, that they might yet in time bethinke themſelues, and turne to the Lord from their euill waies. Be counſelled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Oye rich, &amp; receiue the word of exhortation, make friendes of your vnrighteous Mammon, ſell that you haue and giue almes, <hi>For what auantageth it a man to winne the whole world, and to looſe his owne ſoule?</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:5091:28"/> Attend vnto the voice of him that once ſaide <hi>Woe be vnto you rich for you haue your conſolation.</hi> Wherefore learne to ſuffer ſome affliction heere in this life, that yee bee not afflicted in the world to come: We are taught in the word of God to beare one anothers burden, beare ye therefore ſome part of this croſſe with your poore bretheren that are ſo hardlye preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with pennurie, dearth and famine. Bethink with your ſelues how many good dueties yee haue beene called vnto: how many good occaſions haue bene miniſtred, and how many by you omitted; of euery of which ye ſhal be ſure one day to giue an account. But yet me thinks I heare the voice of Chriſt, ſaying in mine eare, <hi>Tis eaſier for a Camell to goe through the eye of an needle, then for a rich man to enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen,</hi> Yea, but what do the rich men pleade for themſelues in this caſe? namelye thus: that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be vnpoſſible with men, yet not vnpoſſible with God: well, I graunt it, yet I ſay, were it not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a man to make his election ſure and certaine vnto him, then to ſtand vpon poſſibilities? wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlye ſay, better is one bird in hand then two in the buſh; ſo I ſay, it were far better for men to make their election ſure by dooing of good works, while ſpace &amp; grace is offered, then with the fiue fooliſh virgins to runne vp and down from one to another, to buy oyle for their lampes, when none can be had for any money. Who knoweth not that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing impoſſible with God? Chriſt ſaued the theeſe vpon the gallowes repenting; that was one of his poſſibilities, to approoue himſelfe to bee God, but ſhall men therefore play the theeues all the daies of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5091:28"/> their liues, and rob God of his honour, as many doe the poore of their goods, and ſay nothing is vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible with God? is not this rather to tempt God then to ſerue him? to reſiſt the Lord then to obey him? he ſo dayly calling vpon them by the Doctrine of his word to be liberall, to be mercifull, to bee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, kinde, and naturally affected one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yet it cannot be obtained at our hands, nor wrung out of the hearts of many, who are ſo wonne by the world, that they will not leaue off to treaſure vp vengeance for themſelues againſt the day of the wrath of the Lord, who will reward euerye man according vnto his workes: which one found of the Lords Trumpet were ſufficient to make a breach in our obſtinate ſoules (if it were well attended vnto) and to cauſe vs to abhorre ſinne as a Serpent, or at the leaſt to conceiue ſome feare in committing thereof, and continuing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſo reſolute as many do. God for his mercies ſake in Ieſus Chriſt vouchſafe to lighten the eyes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the hearts of thoſe that are either ſo wilfullye blinde or hardned in heart, that they will not ſee nor vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thoſe things which are ſo appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before their faces, that they may in good time bee conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from their euill waies, to ſerue the Lord in all holy obedience and newneſſe of life. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your well willer in the Lord. W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="meditation">
            <pb facs="tcp:5091:29"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5091:29"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Meditation vpon the 26. verſe</hi> of the 11. Chap. of the <hi>Prouerbes;</hi> which may fitly be called, The poore-mans Plea.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pro. 11. verſe. 26.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>He that withdraweth Corne, the people will curſe him, but blesſing ſhall be vpon his head that ſelleth Corne.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ike as for the incitation and ſtirring vp of good men, vnto vertue &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, there are many priuiledges and promiſes ſet downe in Gods worde, for their further encouragement and going forward therein, So againe on the other ſide, for the terrour and reproofe of the wicked, there are many ſentences and ſayings recorded, to the end they might deſiſt &amp; leaue off their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and turne to the Lord their God. Amongſt which, this is one that I haue read vnto you, and yeeldeth moſt euident demonſtration, as in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall parts thereof (which are a curſe and a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) may ealſiy be gathered. For in the firſt part it is ſaide: <hi>He that withdraweth Corne, the people will curſe him:</hi> from whence we may firſt learne, that like as it is not vnlawfull to keepe or lay vp Corne in time of plenty, againſt a time of ſcarſitie, and dearth, or want (as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did in Aegipt) ſo in time of ſcarfitie
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:5091:30"/> and dearth, when we may conueniently ſpare it, &amp; others doe want it, then to with-holde the ſelling of, or to keepe it hutched vp in our barnes, Ricks or Garners, in hope to raiſe the price of it, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich our ſelues by vndooing or famiſhing of others, is a verie inhumane and vnchriſtian part. And this is it, that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> reporteth in this place, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fault at this day, for as wee are taught by the Lawe and the Prophets, <hi>To doe as wee would bee done vnto,</hi> as we reade in <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. verſe 12. Now ſay then that this were thy caſe, or mine, (as it is of manye thouſands) that either of vs did want foode or ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, would we be content ſo to be dealt withall, as to giue or paye double or treble the price for ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as they were vſed to be ſold at, or as in any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie or conſcience they are worth? for ſo are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny compelled to do, or elſe they cannot haue them. And all becauſe that many through couetouſneſſe and crueltie, and hardnes of heart are giuen ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waies to with-drawe their Corne from their Bretheren as they doe. For not only doe they hutch and hide it vp in their Barnes, Rickes, and Garners, not vouchſafing to ſtore the Markets with it as they ought; But alſo when they bring out any, it is in ſo ſcant and pinching a manner and meaſure, and at ſo hie a price, that the poore who moſte do want it, are neuer the neere, beeing not able to compaſſe it. Beſides this, when they cannot ſell it at their own price, that they would haue for it, they ſet it vp, or ſend it home againe, and then tranſport it by water beyond Seas vnto ſome other place of Marte, where they may ſell it at their pleaſure. And by all
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5091:30"/> theſe waies may it be ſaid that they with draw their Corne from the people: as firſt, when they bring it not to the market, ſecondly when they ſell it or hold it at too deere a price, and thirdly when they tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport it to other places: and therefore it were good that all ſuch with-drawers of Corne from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or from the Market, did well conſider of this, that the holy Ghoſt hath heere left recorded for the opening of their hearts, if they be not paſt cure, as I feare me many of them be; for he that doth either miſerably hutch it vp in his Barne, as the rich man mentioned in the 12. of S. <hi>Luke,</hi> that built his barnes bigger, or hold the price ſo hie, that the poore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach it, as many did in the daies of the prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> Chap. 8. 5. ſaying: <hi>When will the new Moone be gone, that we may ſell Corne, and the Saboath, that we may ſet foorth wheate, and make the</hi> Ephah <hi>ſmall, and the</hi> ſhekel <hi>greate, and falſifie the weights by deceit?</hi> or vnneighbourly tranſport it vn to other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or people (as many amongſt vs do at this day) the which how dreadfull and damnable a thing it is, we may learne by theſe manifolde Doctrines and diuine dueties, which Chriſt our Sauiour hath left recorded in his holyword, teaching vs the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. As namely &amp; firſt of all, to be merciful, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith, <hi>Bee mercifull as your heauenly father is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full:</hi> meaning thereby, that wee ſhould rather giue Corne, and other foode franckly and freelye vnto thoſe that want it, then by any cruell and couetous meanes, to with-draw it from them: as our Saniour plainely in an other place ſaith: <hi>Giue to euerie man that asketh, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him that wold borrow, turn not thy face away.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:5091:31"/>
            <p>This alſo was the meaning of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> when he ſaide, <hi>Whoſoeuer hath this worlds goods and ſeeth his brother want, and releeueth him not, how dwelleth the loue of God in him?</hi> Beſide, our <hi>Salomon</hi> heere, v. 25. ſaith to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>That the ſoule of the liberall waxeth fat, and he that giueth plentifully ſhal poure foorth.</hi> As if he would ſay, as we commonly ſay, he ſhall haue neuer the leſſe at the yeres end: yet ſo diffident and diſtruſtfull are many in this caſe, that they will rather ſay with the Prince, mentioned in 2. Reg. 7. 2. who when <hi>Eliza</hi> propheſied of plenty, the day fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, anſwered the man of God thus: <hi>Though the Lord would make windowes in heauen, could this come to paſse?</hi> ſo diffident I ſay are many now adoies, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of theſe withdrawers of Corne, that if a man ſpeake to them in the word of the Lord, that is, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading or exhorting them to liberallitie towards the poore, or vnto deſtributing of their Corne to the needy, at a reaſonable price, by any the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences or ſayings of Chriſt, or manner of his mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles wrought vnto that end (as we may beholde by the encreaſe of the fiue barly-loaues, &amp; two fiſhes, &amp; ſeauen loaues, and a few fiſhes at an other time) they wil anſwer, as the prince before named, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Eliza, Though the Lord would make windowes in heauen &amp;c.</hi> For which cauſe let this be knowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto them, that he which ſoweth ſparingly, ſhall reap ſparingly. As by the example of <hi>Diues</hi> that rich withdrawer of Corne and bread (for by Corne heere, you may vnderſtand bread, drink, cloth, coin, or any ſuch like thing) that would not vouchſafe poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> the cruſtes nor crummes of his tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:5091:31"/> when he lay at his gate, begging for them: how righteouſly was he rewarded againe, when he would haue had of <hi>Abraham</hi> but one drop of water to coole the heat of his tongue, being tormented in hell fire, and could not haue it? a ſpeciall docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or warning to all with-drawers of Corne, Coyne, Cloth, or comfort from their bretheren, in time of neceſſitie and diſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>Other examples are left recorded in Gods word, to this end and purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſtir vp the hard hearts of ſuch pittileſſe perſons, as hauing aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Corne, Cloth, &amp;c. in poſſeſſion, will not, notwithſtanding al that can be ſaide vnto them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from one mite thereof to the periſhing peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this world. I will rehearſe but onely that ſo memorable a fact of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> as it is recorded in Gen. 45. 28. Vnto whome when his brethren came for Corne in time of ſcarſitie and dearth, he not only filled their ſacks with Corn ſufficient, but alſo gaue them their mony backe againe, which they had brought with them. And is this recorded in vaine (troe yé) and not for our imitation, aſwel as for our inſtruction? as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth, ſaying Ro. 15. 4 <hi>Whatſoeuer things are written afore time</hi> (meaning in the word of God) <hi>are written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the Scripture, might haue hope.</hi> But alas, no examples can moue the mindes of mortall men, to depart from this tranſitory traſh, though it were to the ſauing of their ſoules. Earthy men earthly mindes: if men would but lift vp their hearts a little toward the Lord, and beholde the ſenſeleſſe earth with the flowers and fruits therof,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:5091:32"/> conſider the the Sunne, Moone and Starres, how e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one of theſe in their kinde doe yeelde their ſent, ſauour, taſte, light, heate, and comfort to man; it might ſomething mooue them to ſhewe pittie and compaſſion towards their poore brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, ſtanding in neede thereof.</p>
            <p>Of the <hi>Pellican,</hi> (a poore Bird) it is reported, that when ſhee hath brought foorth her young ones, they die, the which when ſhe perceiueth, ſhee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth their death three daies, and then for their recouerie vnto life againe, what doth ſhee? euen ſtab her ſelfe in the breſt with her beake, vntil the blood drop out, which ſhe letting fall vppon her young ones, they doe immediately reuiue againe, but ſhee dies for it her ſelfe.</p>
            <p>What a motiue might this bee to ſuch vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull men, (as wee haue many amongſt vs) that in the like caſe, beholding many of their Bretheren and Siſters, euen (as it were) deade at their doores, or little better, will not droppe nor let fall one pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye out of their Purſes, nor abate one ſhilling of their prices, nor one buſhell of their corne, toward the releefe, comfort, or reuiuing of ſo manye hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger-ſtarued ſoules as daily pine away &amp; periſh, and all by reaſon that they ſo with-drawe their Corne from them ſo many waies as they doe? For reſtraint of whoſe cruel &amp; couetous conceites, let it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered what the holy ghoſt hath heer left recorded, ſaying: <hi>Him that with draweth the Corne, the people will curſe.</hi> But is this ſuch a matter (wil they ſay) to haue the curſſe of the people? what care I for the curſe of a thouſand of them, when all their cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:5091:32"/> wil not doe mee ſo much harme, as one of my buſhels of wheate or Barlie will do me good.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like are the ſpeeches of thoſe whoſe hearts are glewed to their golde, corne, and earthly commodities, in ſuch wiſe as that they make them their God, and ſo care not for the counſell of the Lord their God. But like as it was once to that great with-drawer of corne mentioned, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 18. whoſe grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d brought forth fruits plentiouſly, in ſo much that hee ſaide, <hi>What ſhall I doe, becauſe I haue not roome where I may lay vp my fruites? and hee ſaide, this will I doe, I will pull downe my Barnes,</hi> (as manye ſet vp their ricks for like purpoſe) <hi>and builde greater, and therein will I gather my fruites, and my goods. And I will ſay to my Soule, thou hast much goods laide vp in store for manye yeares, liue at eaſe, eate, drinke, and take thy pastime</hi> (or as wee ſay) be merrie, and make good cheere, as many doe at this day: but what was ſaid to him in the end? <hi>God ſaide to him, O foole, this night will they fetch away thy ſoule from thee: then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be that thou haſt prouided?</hi> So it is with him that gathereth riches to himſelfe, and is not rich towards God, and ſo it is with al theſe, none ſo merrie with-drawers of corn, ſellers, or ſenders away therof, they are now Iocond and merrie, but the time will come, when they ſhall mourne and lament.</p>
            <p>And heere it is worth the nothing, that the Text faith. <hi>They ſhall fetch away thy Soule,</hi> whereby is ment the Deuill and his Angells: for like as it is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of <hi>Lazarus</hi> that pore begger when he died, that he was caried by the Angels into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:5091:33"/> but of the rich man there me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned, the firſt newes that we heare of him after he was dead, he was in hell torments. Let euery one therefore that liueth in his pleaſures, or couetous deſires (as this rich man did, and as many other rich men doe at this preſent) make good vſe heere of and take heed of withdrawing their Corne, Cloth, Coyne, or any thing els, from their poore bretheren: for, ſay they liue neuer ſo pleaſantly or happy, in the mean time the people do curſe them, which althogh they care litle for; yet behold how great &amp; grieuous a thing it is to haue the peoples curſ deſeruedly: for although it be ſaide pro. 26. 2. <hi>The curſe cauſeles commeth not, or ſhal not hurt:</hi> yet the curſe that is cauſed deſerued<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by crueltie, oppreſſion, couetouſnes, or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde of rigorous dealing, or violent meanes, ſhal not paſſe with out perril &amp; paine. For why, the reaſon is euident: the poore crie and the Lord hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them, pſ. 10. 17. as if he would ſay, he reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them, as he did the Iſraelites againſt the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptians,</hi> we commonly ſay, a common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Vox populi, vox dei,</hi> that is, the voice of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is the voyce of God, or that which the people doe moſt agree vpon or ſpeake is the voice of God, q. d. whome the multitude did curſe, God himſelfe doth curſe. For as he is curſed of God that remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the land marke, that is the Mereſtone or ridge of his neighbour, ſo as he that remooueth or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draweth the Corne from the people: at the leaſt we muſt take it for a grieuous plague, to be iuſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted or perſecuted with the outcries of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for like as a good name is mote ptetious then
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:5091:33"/> oyntment, and to be preferd before gold or ſiluer: So to be iuſtly reproached, maligned, or curſed of the people is a thing very loathſome and worſe then the loſſe of any worldly thing beſide, as it is well noted by the holy ghoſt in this place. The laſt of al Gods iudgements againſt ſinners, &amp; the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt is, <hi>Ite maledicti,</hi> that is, go ye curſed: that's Gods curſe: from whence we may learne, how grieuous a thing the curſe of man is. Euen the greateſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance or iniury that man can doe to man, as we may gather by the words of <hi>Iobs</hi> wife, who ſeing her husband plagued, her goods and children deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, bids him curſe God and dye: As if ſhe would haue ſayd, ſpit out all thy venome or, ſeeing thou canſt doe nothing els in the way of reuenge, curſe God and die. Like vnto that of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> who when he pluckt downe the pillar of the Temple, ſlewe both himſelfe and the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> alſo. For what doth a man or a woman intend, or mean, or deſire, when they curſe their neighbour or aduerſary, but euen the greateſt miſchiefe, plague, or puniſhment that they can deuiſe in the bitternes of their ſoules, to light vpon him or her whome they curſe.</p>
            <p>And therefore, it is recorded of the holy ghoſt in <hi>Iude,</hi> v. 9. as a caueat to all chriſtians, to take heed of curſing others, or cauſing others to curſe them. By the example of <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangell, who when he ſtroue about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> would not blame him with curſed ſpeaking, but only ſaid <hi>The Lord rebuke thee.</hi> But happily heere ſome will demaund how it falleth out that the deere Saints and ſeruants of God do many times feele the ſtroak
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:5091:34"/> of this ſting, I meane the curſe of the people? for anſwere whereunto, it is not ſo much to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered who are curſed (for all are ſubiect ro the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the tongue) (as we ſee by Chriſt himſelfe) as wherefore they are curſed: for if it be for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, or reproouing of ſinne, it commeth not, but is a bleſſing rather, as our Sauiour ſheweth it ſaying, Mat. 5. 11. <hi>Bleſſed are ye, when men reuile you, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute you, and ſhall falſely ſay all manner of euill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt youfor my names ſake, &amp;c.</hi> for in this caſe, they are bleſſed of God himſelfe: but if it be for ſecret ſinnes againſt God, or for open iniuries, oppreſſions, and treſpaſſes againſt our neighbours; then let them take heed leaſt (as they ſay) God ſay Amen: for although it be heere ſaid, <hi>The people will curſe him,</hi> yet as it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by <hi>Dauid,</hi> 2. Sam. 16. v. 10. 11. God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe dooth permit and ſuffer it, it being his iuſt iudgement againſt ſuch perſons as haue ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. The which the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, would not ſuffer <hi>Shimei,</hi> when he curſed him to be ſmitten, but rather ſaide, <hi>What if God hath bidden him, it may be that God will looke upon mine afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and do me good for his curſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Moſes</hi> maketh manifeſt in the 27. of Deu. where he denounceth euen from God himſelfe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorts of people accurſed, which would not walk in the waies of the almightie, but tranſgreſſe his commaundements: as thus, <hi>Curſed is he that curſeth father or mother: curſed is he that maketh the blinde to goe out of his way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This dooth Saint <hi>Iames</hi> alſo confirme, ſaying, that ſuch men as hourd vp their riches, garments,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:5091:34"/> gold or ſiluer, or with-hold the wages of the hireling euen til it ruſt or canker by them, or the moath doth fret or eat it, hauing no compaſſion on the poore that want it, are no better then accurſed with the reſt, euen of God him ſelfe, as appeareth by his words, Chap. 5. v. 1. 2. 3. ſaying, <hi>Goe to now ye rich men, weepe and howle for the miſeries that ſhall come upon you: your riches are corrupt, your garments are moath-ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, your gold and ſiluer is cankered, and the ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſſe againſt you, and ſhall eat your fleſh as it were with fire, ye haue heaped vp treaſure againſt the laſt daies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if he would ſay, ye are accurſed all and euery one of you, like as they that with-draw their Corne from the poore, and keepe it in their Barnes, Rickes, or Garners, vntill it be ſo mouldie or fuſtie, that the Rats and Mice wil ſcant eat it. Therefore let them take good heed, I meane al cruel &amp; couetous Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breeders, buyers, Cornemaſters, corne-mongers, cloath-maiſters, and euery other pinching penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, who are ſuch louers of themſelues, and ſhew ſo little pittie towards others, not withſtanding that they ſwim in their Superfluities and aboundance of all wordly treaſures and pleaſures, do not ſo much as bring forth their corne, coyne, nor cloath nor any thing els to releeue them that want, and ſtand in deſtres.</p>
            <p>But haply, it may heere be ſaide, are there not many good lawes and orders made for the releeuing and keeping of the poore in euery Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and euery Pariſh hath ouer-ſeeers, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide them harbour and ſuſtenance? yes it is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:5091:35"/> ſo I graunt, and yet for all this, the poorelie ſtill &amp; complaine in vaine, without both houſe-roome and food. Though the King make his ſtatute, and the Iuſtice ſend his precept, yet ſaith Chriſt, <hi>The poore ye ſhall haue alwaies with you,</hi> and ſo we haue, as poore as euer were, and as I ſuppoſe neuer more: and all by reaſon of ſuch with-drawers of Corn, as be now a daies many amongſt vs; who notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the people do daily curſe them, and the Lord doth curſe them, and the deuill be ready to fetch them; yet there is no compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, pittie, nor redreſſe. But what will all theſe with-drawers of Corne, and with-holders of comfort from the poore do, when he ſhall come in place that ſhal ſay vnto them, <hi>when I was naked ye cloathed me not, when I was hungry ye fed me not, when I was harbourleſſe ye houſed me not,</hi> nor ſo much as vouchaſafed me a nights lodging in their Barnes, &amp;c. <hi>Goe ye curſed into hell fire prepared for the Deuill and his angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if God reward theſe with-drawers of Corn ſo heauily, that famiſh or ſtarue the bodies of their bretheren and ſiſters, by with-drawing or keeping from them their corporall foode, what will he do to thoſe that with-draw and with-hold from them the ſpiritual foode of their ſoules? and do not break to them the bread of life, I meane that do not preach the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt; hauing recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a talent that way, or holding the place of ſuch as ſhould do it? An Item to all Parſons, Vicars, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, and Fermors of ſpirituall liuings, which liue by the ſweat of other mens ſoules; &amp; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo muzzell vp the mouth of the Oxe that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:5091:35"/> treadeth out the Corne, that where the Parſonage is many times worth two or three hundreth pounds by the yeare, the Oxe I ſay that treadeth out the Corne, that is, the Miniſter that breaketh and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the foode that periſheth not, hath not aboue ten pounds or twenty markes by the yeare, and that but ſorily paid too: If this be not a with-drawing of Corne and all other neceſſaries, I can not tell what is.</p>
            <p>O conſider this, ye that ſwallowe vp the poore, and make the needy of the land to faile. Theſe are ſuch with-drawers as ye heard of euen now, that hyre labourers to reap downe their fields and then will not pay them their wages. O King conſider: O King of Kings remember thy choſen flocke, and ſend vs ſome releefe, I meane thy choſen Iſraell from all our paine and griefe. O conſider this both prieſt and people, for where the word of God is not preached, the people periſh, not in body but in ſoule, as the apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> proueth plainly: ſaying <hi>How can they call on him in vvhome they haue not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: hovv can they beleeue in him of whome they haue not heard? how can they heare vvithout a preacher? hovv can they preach except they be ſent?</hi> Ro. 10. 14. And yet ſo mindefull is he of his promiſe, that once ſaid, <hi>I am with you to the end of the world,</hi> that now and ſtill he ſaith vnto his little flocke <hi>Beholde I ſend vnto you Prophets, and vviſemen, and Scribes,</hi> &amp; what followes? thus, <hi>and of them you ſhall kill and crucifie, and ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhal ſcourge in your Sinagogues</hi> (not with whips of cords, ſo much as with the whips of your whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping) tongues, <hi>and of them you ſhall perſecute from Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:5091:36"/> 
               <hi>to Cittie. &amp;c.</hi> and who do all this now adaies, but theſe with-drawers of Corn, which with-draw not onely from the market, but from the miniſter; not onely from the poore, but from the preacher, and from the church and all: may I not complaine with the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> 7. 8. once again &amp; ſay; <hi>Shall not the land tremble for this. &amp; eueryone mourn that dwell ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? and it ſhall riſe vp as a flood, and it ſhall be caſt out and drowned, as by the flood of Aegipt,</hi> that is, deſtroyed with one iudgement or other. It followes, <hi>But bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſhalbe vpon his head that ſelleth corne.</hi> Hitherto ye haue heard of the curſe that commeth downe on the heads of the with-drawers either of Corn from the poore people or of mainteinance from the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. Now of the bleſſing that belongeth to both or all of them, that ſell their Corne at a reaſonable rate, and in due time, or breake the bread of life, or giue competent mainteinance to the Miniſter. And firſt, whereas <hi>Salomon</hi> ſeemeth to vtter his ſpeeche in the ſingular number, as appeereth by the words, <hi>Blesſing,</hi> and, <hi>his head,</hi> yet it ſhal appeere vnto you, that they include and comprehend, both a plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of bleſſings, and a multiplicitie of heads, or parts both of ſoule and body: for ſuch is the wiſedome of God, that vnder the number of few words, yea &amp; thoſe moſt commonly darke and obſcure (to the naturall man) are conteined many miſteries, much doctrine, and great knowledge: as we ſee in Chriſt his parrables, ſweet ſentences, and holy ſermons, vttered in the goſpell: and all to this end, that like as we ſay a man muſt cracke the Nut before he can eat the kirnell, ſo he would haue vs to ſtudy, pray,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:5091:36"/> meditate &amp; exerciſe our ſelues in the word of God before we can come to the depth of knowledge &amp; vnderſtanding of his truth. This our Sauiour ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth manifeſt, in <hi>Mat. 13. v. 11.</hi> and 13. ſaying, <hi>To you it is giuen to know the miſteries or ſecrets of the kingdome of heauen,</hi> q. d. To you my deſciples that followe me, and heare my voice, and doe ſeeke for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, <hi>But blesſing ſhalbe vpon his head,</hi> or bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, for God is not as man, who when he hath bleſſed one, can bleſſe no more as <hi>Iſaac</hi> bleſſed <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> and after had ſcant a bleſſing for <hi>Eſaw,</hi> But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as <hi>Moſes,</hi> who, when he had bleſſed one tribe, bleſſed an other, and neuer left vntill he had bleſſed them all. Or as Chriſt himſelfe, who when he had pronounced the poore in ſpirit bleſſed; he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to the pure in hart, then to the meeke, then to the mourners, hungrie and thirſtie, mercifull, peacemakers, and patient; and pronounced them all bleſſed. Euen ſo here, though he ſpake in the ſinguler number, ſaying. Bleſſing <hi>ſhalbe vppon the heade:</hi> yet, he meaneth many bleſſings, or that he ſhalbe many waies bleſſed, according as he hath promiſed vnto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaying, <hi>If thou ſhalt obay dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently the voice of the Lord thy God, and obſerue and do all his commandements which I haue commaunded thee this day, the Lord thy God, will ſet thee vp on high aboue all nations of the earth, and all theſe blesſings ſhall come vpon thee: Bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the Cittie, and bleſſed in the fielde, bleſſed ſhalt thou he in the fruit of thy body, and of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28. 1. 3 &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>thy ground, bleſsed in thy cattell, and in the encreaſe of thy kine, and in the flockes of thy ſheepe &amp;c. and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhalt thou be in all that thou putteſt thy hand vnto.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:5091:37"/>
            <p>Thus we ſee how many waies almightie God bleſſeth all thoſe that keepe his commaundements: This the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> confirmeth, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed is the man that conſidereth the poore and needy, the Lord ſhall deliuer him in the time of trouble. Yea, the Lord will helpe him and preſerue him aliue. He ſhalbe bleſſed vpon earth, and thou wilt not deliuer him vnto the will of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. The Lord will ſtrengthen him on the bed of his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, &amp; make his bed in his ſicknes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, as by this we learne, what bleſſings ſhalbe on the head, heart, and ſoule of ſuch a man, as mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth comfort vnto them that be in neceſſitie. So on the other part we may gather what curſes ſhall come on ſuch as with-drawe corne, coyne, or comfort from them by any manner of meanes. For like as it is ſaid of the mercifull man, <hi>The Lord ſhall deliuer him &amp;c. the Lord ſhall bleſſe him on earth and not betake to the will of his enemies:</hi> ſo contrarywiſe ſhall it befall the vnmerciful, that haue no bowels of pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie nor compaſſion in them. Letthe example of holy <hi>Iob</hi> be our comfort in this caſe, who was a ſtaſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lame, an eye vnto the blinde, and a father vnto the fatherles, &amp;c. All which his kindenes how the Lord requited, and what end he made, who knoweth not? Vnto this patterne of pittie, I might ad the examples of <hi>Abraham, Lot,</hi> the <hi>Shunamite</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Lidia, Cornelius</hi> and the reſt, whoſe charitie, hoſpitalitie, kindenes, and comforting the needy members of Ieſus chriſt, is yet much ſpoken off &amp; recorded in holy writ vnto this end, and for the ſame ſhall be had in an euerlaſting remembrance. Let vs therefore heerewithal looke vp on the Naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gators
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:5091:37"/> and Seafaring men of this world, who for the preſeruation of their liues in time of tempeſt or danger on the Sea, doe not ſticke to caſt out their Corne, or whatſoeuer commoditie elſe they haue ballaſt their Ships withall, although it bee to their great detriment and loſſe, rather then they will loſe their liues. And ſhall not Chriſtian men ſayling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt the manifold tempeſts of this world, and the temptations of this life, in the greateſt danger of their ſoules, vnballaſt their Barnes of that which ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth behinde the doore in the Chaffe? I doe not ſee with what words I may better reprooue their hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of heart, then with that verſe that the Poet <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> made vpon the like conſideration, &amp; exclaming after this manner: <hi>O curuae in terr as animae et celeſtium inanes!</hi> that is, O crooked ſoules vpon earth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide of heauenly things. Againe, if men would but conſider with themſelues, how willing and forward they are many times in purging, caſting foorth and cutting off the verie ſubſtantial parts and humors of their bodies, being either infected with ſome incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable diſeaſe, or otherwiſe corrupted through ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much aboundance and all for the preſeruation and continuance of their temporall and momentarie liues, it might happily moone them, to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing &amp; laying out of theſe other inferior things, for the ſaluation of their ſoules. Aman would think that ſo many examples of ſo many holy men &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, might allure and procure vs to change our mindes, &amp; to ſet our affections on heauenly things, or elſe that ſo many coſifels of Chriſt himſelf would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraine vs to make vs friends of our vnrighteous
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:5091:38"/> Mammon, or that rich and heauenly bleſſing which Chriſt ſhall beſtow on all thoſe that haue releeued his needy members, and comforted the comfortles, when he ſhall ſay to them, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my father and poſseſſe the kingdome prepared for you from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world, For when I was naked ye cloathed mee, when I was hungrie ye fed me, when I was harhourleſſe yee houſed me, when I was ſicke and diſeaſed ye viſited and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed mee with Corne, coyne, cloath, and all other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts.</hi> And if they ſhall anſwere and ſay, <hi>when ſawe wee thee naked and cloathed thee, or hungry and fed thee, or ſicke and viſited thee.</hi> &amp;c. Then ſhall he anſwere them againe, and ſay to them, <hi>In as much as ye haue done it to one of theſe little ones which haue beleeued in me, ye haue done it vnto me, Come ye bleſsed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5091:38"/>
            <head>To the indifferent Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven as I had finiſhed this tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, there came vnto mee cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine perſons of the Countie and confines where I dwelled, with a written Paper in their hands, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying therein what paines and coſt they had vndertaken, and what troubles they had endured in ſeeking to redeſſe, or at the leaſt to reſtraine the Tranſportation of Corne, and all other victualls, (fruite on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly except) from the Townes of <hi>Bewdley, Tewxburie,</hi> and the Citties of <hi>VVorceſter</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> vnto <hi>Briſtowe,</hi> &amp;c. wherein alſo it appeared, that by the good meanes &amp; care of ſome of the higher powers; they had obtained Letters of commannd to the Iuſtices of Peace within the countie of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> to appoint certaine honeſt and
<pb facs="tcp:5091:39"/> ſubſtantiall men to be ſearchers of all ſuch boates or veſſels as ſhould paſſe on the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of Seauerne, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of the foreſaid pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to another place, by which good means it hath pleaſed God ſomewhat to mittigate the dayly encreaſing price of corn &amp; graine amongſt vs.</p>
            <p>But for as much as it was giuen mee, to vnderſtand at the ſame time, by thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that came to ſollicit this cauſe; that the moſt part of thoſe perſons ſo appointed by the Iuſtices to be ſearchers, were very weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy men; that is to ſay either great Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſters, or cloathiers, &amp; therfore for their owne parts, had no greate cauſe to indure the paines, which was needeful in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to bee taken; &amp; the reſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being of meaner condition &amp; ſtate and therfore not ſo wel able to beare the daily charges about this employment (as beeing more deſirous to haue it better effected, then the reſt) craued the Aſsiſtance of the Pariſhes and Towne-ſhippes adioyning, by ſome beneuolent collection, for the ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their expences, promiſing with all, a more diligent and dayly attendance vppon
<pb facs="tcp:5091:39"/> the ſaid ſearch. The which their ſo honeſt, needfull, and neceſſarie a Petition, I not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſentlye tendered to make knowne; but alſo for the better continuance therof, I thought good to giue ſome intelligence heerein, that euerie good Chriſtian, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regardeth the crie of the poore, or the loue of his Neighbour, may put to his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping hand, to ſo good and charitable an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wherefore now in as much as it hath pleaſed God by the Doctrine of his word to giue vs the true knowledge and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the verie originall cauſe of this preſent dearth, and both opened and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto vs the meanes to preuent and take away the ſame; Let vs not be ſlacke to ioyne both heart and hand, purſe and prayer, minde &amp; money for the ſpeedy redreſsing of this euill, ſo iuſtly impoſed and laide vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, for ſuch cauſes as haue bene by vs committed.</p>
            <p>God graunt that wee bee not receiuers of the grace of God in vaine, nor turne his gace into Wantonneſſe, leaſt while we ſay peace, peace, the Lord of Hoſtes come
<pb facs="tcp:5091:40"/> againſt vs with his great Armie, the ſound of a Trumpet, voice of an Arch-an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, conſuming fire, and ſuch like.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
